<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Onosandro Platonico, of the generall captaine, and of his office, translated out of Greeke into Italyan, by Fabio Cotta, a Romayne: and out of Italian into Englysh, by Peter Whytehorne</title>
            <title>Strategicus. English</title>
            <author>Onasander.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1563</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 164 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 94 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08491</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18815</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S120944</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99856135</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99856135</idno>
            <idno type="VID">21658</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08491)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21658)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1322:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Onosandro Platonico, of the generall captaine, and of his office, translated out of Greeke into Italyan, by Fabio Cotta, a Romayne: and out of Italian into Englysh, by Peter Whytehorne</title>
                  <title>Strategicus. English</title>
                  <author>Onasander.</author>
                  <author>Whitehorne, Peter.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 136, [8] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By William Seres. Cum priuilegio ad imprimendum solum,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno. 1563.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation, by Peter Whitehorne, of: Strategicus.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Military art and science --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:21658:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21658:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Onoſandro Platonico, of the Generall Captaine, and of</hi> his office, tranſlated out of Greke into Italyan, by Fabio Cotta, a Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayne: and out of I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talian into Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyſh, by Peter QWyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horne</p>
            <p>¶ Imprinted at London, by Willyam Seres.</p>
            <p>¶ <hi>Cum priuilegio ad impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendum ſolum, Anno. 1563.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:21658:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21658:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>TO THE HIGH AND myghtye Prince, Thomas Duke of Northfolke, Earle Marſhall of Englande, knyght of the moſt noble order of the Garter, and one of the Queenes Maieſties priny Counſel, Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> VVhitehorne, wyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth longe lyfe with perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>VHat great commoditye</hi> and profytte (ryght worthy Prince) hath alwayes redounded to the weale publy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes and gouernours of the ſame, which in warlike diſcipline haue chiefly delited, and taken greateſt care, and to what excellent fame and renowine, it hath alwayes broughte and exalted (yea from vile and abiect fortune) thoſe that haue moſte trauayled and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuored
<pb facs="tcp:21658:3"/>them ſelues therin, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by alſo wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, haue made notable and wonderful conqueſtes, of ſuch as haue lytle regarded Marſhiall knowledge, the Hiſtorye of the Amazons, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> infinite other, doth manifeſtlye and plainelie declare. And ſpecially the ſame of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maynes, who firſte from poore ſhepeherdes, throughe their pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent ſkil in feates of Armes, ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed their kyngdome, and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchie, that in ſhorte time, they became Lordes, and Emperours of all the world. For by ſuche ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence vndoubtedly, not only forren Countreis are brought in ſubiec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but alſo their owne proper kyngdomes are kept from outra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious crueltie, &amp; rauenous ſpoyle of the ennemies: and good lawes there eſtablyſhed, are quietly exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted vpon offenders, without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellious diſturbaunce. And ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:21658:3"/>the comming vp of the Turkes and the occaſion of their maruey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous victoryes, is well to be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtande to haue happened by no other meanes, but onelye, for that there is no nation in al the world, with whome they haue warred, whiche in all kinde of Marſhiall affayres and doinges, ſo much re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembleth, and imitateth the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous antiquitie, as they: whiche partlye I am able to witnes, by that I haue ſene, when I was in Conſtantinople, and in Turkie. Which thing conſideringe with my ſelfe, and of late happening in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to my handes, the copie of thys booke, called Onoſandro Plato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nico. Who many yeres agon, moſt excellentlye in the Greke tounge, wrote of the offyce of a Generall Capitaine, whiche longe agon I didde tranſlate out of the Italion tounge for mine owne exerciſe, and
<pb facs="tcp:21658:4"/>for the great delight that I haue alwayes had in the ſtudiynge of the arte of war, I haue thought good at this preſent, for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon vtilitie of my countreymen, who delyte in warlyke ſkilfulnes, to ſufter the ſame to be publyſhed in printe. In whiche booke is to be founde, as good aduiſes, and counſels, for a Captayne, or man of warre, as can poſſibly be inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted or imagined. Wherefore, for as muche as youre Grace, right no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blye and valiauntly, hath hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore executed the office of a Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall, wherin alſo the worthie actes of youre Noble Graundfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, is of moſte ſhynynge and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous remembraunce, I could not deuiſe with my ſelfe, vnto whom this my labour and trauaile, was more meete to be dedicated vnto, then to your Grace, who in Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhiall feates, and in the profounde
<pb facs="tcp:21658:4"/>knowledge thereof, is thought moſte expert. And although my tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſlation herin, be very rude and groſſe, yet becauſe my good wyll with the effect and worthines of the matter is chiefly to be wayed and conſidered, my truſte is, that accordynge to youre accuſtomed gentelneſſe, you wyll accept the ſame in good part: conſideringe that groſſe phraſes, cannot in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitye maime a good meaning, no more, then the exellent entent of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lawes of this Realme, is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny whit abaſed through the vnſauery lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, wherin they are writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:21658:5"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21658:5"/>
            <head>ONOSANDRO PLA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonico, of the General Captaine, and of his offyce, vnto Quintus <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranius, a Romaine.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Arte and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of rydinge, of hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynge, of fyſhing, and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally of tillynge the fiel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, I iudge ought to be written to thoſe, which in ſuch ſtudies are wont ineſpecially to delyght. But the waye to come to conſider the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of a General Captaine, I ſuppoſe (O Quintus <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>eranius) that aboue al other, is moſte conuenyent to the Romaynes: and chyeflye to thoſe, which of reputacion, and Senate au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, be ſuperiours to others. And lykewyſe it is meete for ſuche, as by the iudgement of Auguſtus Ceſar, and for the true knowledge that they haue of ſuch an office, and for the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guler experience of thinfinyte &amp; moſte weighty affaires, and alſo for the dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitye and worthynes of their prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſours, haue had fortune to ſuccede the honourable degrees, aſwel of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuls,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:21658:6"/>as of Captaynes: Therefore I iudge, that to ſuche maner of menne, ought to be dedicated like worke: but not after ſuche ſort, as thoughe they knewe not howe to rule and gouerne Armyes: For in dede the cauſe whye I am moued to write, is ſpecially for this reſpecte, ſeynge that many, the more they be ignoraunt, and leſſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pert of things, making of other mens doynges ſeldome iuſt iudgement, ſo muche the more preſumptuouſly, they continuallye perceuer, both to repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bend and to ſlaunder good captaines: Where thoſe truly that haue experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and knowledge of thinges, with good reſpect, beholdinge the worthye &amp; honorable enterpriſes of other, haue wyth high prayſe, commended them. Wherefore although I knowe that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> matter which I haue purpoſed to wrie may ſeme to many to haue ben a great while agon heretofore thought vpon &amp; fully knowen: yet for all that, I wil not leaue of to bring to an end my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termination: but rather more pro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptly I ſhal perſeuer to proced forwards, as he that not only may ſeme to geue in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions profytable to Captaynes, but alſo as one that knoweth after
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:21658:6"/>what ſort thei ought to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maund. And I ſhall worthely repute my ſelfe hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py, yf I be thought mete to manifeſt with words, thoſe thynges, which the Romaynes by meanes of their vertue and of their induſtry, moſt valiantlye brought to paſſe. For the which thing if I maye vnderſtande that this my paines are commended and approued of like men: I ſhall then be able to ſay that in this preſent worke, is contay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the counſels of renowmed Capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains in this happy time of peace. For which cauſe, if no other thinge, at leſt wiſe the ſame may principally aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe and learne you, for what occaſion hath happened vnto ſome, often times moſt vnfortunately to fayght, and to fall into miſery, and howe other ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing brought to good effecte their af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fayres, haue got illuſtrious fame and immortall glorye. As in the ende the ſame ſinguler ercellencye of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines, hath clerelye made manifeſt: for that neuer Kynge, nor Citye, nor yet, neuer Nation, coulde not come to obtayne greater, nor to the lyke equall greatneſſe of their Empire. After ſuche ſorte, that nowe ſo longe time ſemes, that continuall ſo
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:21658:7"/>great largenes of dominion, they haue kept moſt conſtantlye, ſtedfaſtlye, and ſure. Nor I cannot with any maner of reaſon perſwade my ſelfe, that it hath hapned eyther by chaunce, or fortune, that ouer paſſynge the confines of Italye, the name and Empire myght haue bene extended, to the vttermoſte partes of the worlde: but that ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it hath come to paſſe, by prudence by counſell, and by the feates of war, and alſo by the famouſnes, and by the glory of actes moſt valiauntly done. And in dede, where as we ought to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to haue fortune fauourable to our enterpriſes, notwithſtanding it is not to be iudged, that ſhe hath rule ouer euery thinge, and that ſhe is Lady in all matters. And as they that attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute all infelicitye onelye to fortune, and not vnto the negligence &amp; error of Captaines, be fooles and ignorantes, ſo likewiſe be thoſe, whiche thinges directly and with order done, aſſigne it only vnto fortune, and nothinge at al vnto vertue, and to the diligence of the Captayne. And ſurely it is a to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of a malicious, and vniuſt man, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther altogether to clere him from eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry faulte that hath euill miniſtred the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:21658:7"/>publyke affaires, imputinge it to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, or to depriue him from deſerued praiſe, the which valiantly &amp; with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry, hath ouercome and brought to good paſſe his deſire, iudging that the glory of the enterpriſe well and vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>auntly executed, ought to be attribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted onlye vnto fortune. But almoſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery man, being inclined to geue con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence to them that declare or wryte thoſe thinges, of the which they be er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pert, albeit that it ſeme they rehearſe thinges high and difficult to be done, and on the contrarye part, cannot be brought to geue credit to thoſe that ſhewe them any thinge, in the whiche they haue not ben exerciſed, although it be neyther difficulte, nor incredible: Therfore I ſuppoſe it ſhalbe neceſſary for me, firſt to tell you, that what ſo euer in thys booke I haue to wryte of the Captayne, and of the aduertyſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes of warre, hath bene approued with moſt manifeſt experience of thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and in eſpecially of thoſe, whiche were patrons, &amp; Princes, of the name of the Romaines, whoſe excellent ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue without doubt, amongſt all naci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, by the conſent of all menne, euen to this tyme, hath obtayned hygheſt
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:21658:8"/>dignity. Then in this my litle booke, there is not to be comprehended any thinge done vnaduiſedly, in haſte, at all aduentures, nor raſhelye: but that which in varietie of thinges, the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maynes with ſage and firme counſell egregiouſlye wrought and approued. The which not only had true knowe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> was to be don againſt the enemy: but grauely did forſee that they might not in anye maner of wyſe take harme. Nor it ſhall neuer bee found, that they haue vſed other then a ſure order, &amp; iuſt occaſion to faight. I haue therfore gathered fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theſe foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines euery thing y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> I haue written: Albeit that I am fully perſwaded, that many would deſire, that al that which of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> might be ſpoken about ſuch mat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter, ſhuld be eſtemed rather their own proper inuention, then taken of other: as they, who beleue they ſhoulde at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne to greater prayſe, where ſhould appeare that of theym ſuche thinges hath bene firſte found and publyſhed: then if openly they ſhould confeſſe it, not to be theirs, and to haue n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>de of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Authours to attribute it. Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding for this ſelfe ſame occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, I doe thinke to get prayſe &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendacion:
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:21658:8"/>for as much as lyke as he the whiche peraduenture went to the warres, where he hathe wrytten the valiaunt Actes of other, ought not to be depriued of glory, he hauynge lefte written vnto the poſteritye, not thoſe thinges, that with his proper force he had founde &amp; executed, but that which other had done, euen ſo I ſuppoſe not to be a little prayſed, and commended plainlye confeſſyng theſe thynges not to be inuented by me: yea by ſuche occaſion I maye ſeeme not vniuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye to goe about to excell all other, where I ought to report the prayſe of other men without enuy, and trueth, without diſprayſe, and withoute anye maner of blame.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>Of electynge a Capytayne.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Say then, that a Generall captaine ought to be choſen without ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge anye reſpect vnto his ſtock, or vnto his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diceſſors, or vnto goods of fortune: the one of the whyche thynges is the eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome obſerued in the chooſynge of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:21658:9"/>Prieſtes, the other in creating the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidents of plaies, and publike feaſtes. But ſuche a manne is to bee ſought, who is temperate, continente, ſobre, abſtinent, and not exceſſiue in eating and drynking, pacient in trauaile, of witte prompt, not couetous, neyther yong, nor olde, and that he haue chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, if ſuche a one may be had, and to be a faire ſpeaker, of good name and ſame, and of muche reputacion. The cauſe why he ought to be temperate, is, leſt being inlured &amp; geuen to plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, he doe forſake the care of thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, that be of moſt great importance. Continent it behoueth him to be, the which hath bene preferred to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninge of ſo muche importaunce: for that yf the vyolence of an vnbrideled minde, chaunſe to haue power and ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie to doe what ſo euer ſhall pleaſe him, it is after ſuche ſorte with wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe ouerwhelmed, that it cannot eaſely be refrayned. I woulde haue hym alſo to be ſobre, to the ende that more commodiouſly, he might be vigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> affayres of ſo great waight. For that in the time of night, by qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etnes of mind, the counſels of captai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes exammed, more perfectly may the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:21658:9"/>be confirmed. The cauſe that he ought to be abſtinent &amp; content with ſimple fare: is, for aſmuch as the preparyng of diiſhes ful of delicatenes, &amp; the too muche diligence and thought aboute meates, corrupteth and drowneth the minde after ſuch ſorte, that the tyme which ought to haue bene ſpent in the buſines that is to be done, by the dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catenes of the capitaines, moſt vainly is conſumed. The cauſe why he ought to be moſt painful, is, for that princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pallye it doth apperteine to the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, that he in the turmoyles of the war, maye be the laſt to be werye.</p>
            <p>He ought to be quicke witted, for as muche as it behoueth him to be ſwift, and (as Homer ſaith) flyinge, to thend that with his thought, he maye moſt quicklye diſcurſe euerye thinge, and with his minde make iudgement, and as it were deuine, &amp; a far of, forſee that which is to come. Leaſt whiles there happen accidentes, neyther foreſeene nor looked for, the Captaine be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrayned ſodenly, and vnprouided for, to take counſell, and the ſafegarde of thinges to commit moſt fearefully, to the diſcretion of fortune. It behoueth him not to be couerous nor deſireful of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:21658:10"/>gaine. For ſurely of this vice he ought moſte principallye to take heve. For aſmuche as, he that is not geuen to paſſe muche of gyftes, of Syluer, and golde, maye moſt honorably haue the charge of ſuche doinges. And oute of doubt, there be ſome the which with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out anye whit fearing, for highe cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage and luſtynes of body, were apte to wythſtand the armyes and power of enemies: notwithſtanding (they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come moſte vyle) whileſt they be dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen with the vnſaciablenes of golde, the whyche is a weapon of ſo muche mighte to take, and as it were wyth lyuely force, to pul the victorye out of ſuche mens handes, and to gyue it to other. I haue ſayde that the Capitain muſt be neither old nor yong, for that the one, is to muche obſtinate not to beleue, the other is weake in doinges, and neyther the one, nor the other is mete for the rule of thinges. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, me thinks, that the yong man is to be refuſed, to thende that by euill chaunce vndeſcretelye through he ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much boldnes he happen not to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit error. On the contrarye, it is not fitte to admit the olde manne, leaſt he for his natural weakenes, be not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient.
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:21658:10"/>For the whiche cauſe, let vs iudge it beſt that age, that is in the middes betwene the one, and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: becauſe that then, there is force and ſtrength, the which is not as yet ſpent nor conſumed with age: &amp; pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence is founde in him, that is not ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry yonge. And ſurely if any manne in this thinge will approue the luſtines and ſtrength of the body, without the prudence of the minde: or lykewiſe the witte without ſtrength. I am certayn he ſhall doe nothing that ſhalbe well: for aſmuche as lyke as the bodye, that lacketh prudence, is lyttle worth to counſel, euen ſo the mind of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtrength of body, as from miniſters abandoned cannot commodiuſly take in hande to do any attempt, nor with profit bring it to effecte. But he that hath bothe theſe qualities, ſhalbe mete to execute euery enterpriſe. For that to him, as frely beloued of all men, both with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teere affection of minde, when he ſhal commaunde, moſt redely they will o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey, geuinge full truſte vnto his wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, and to what ſoeuer perill he ſhall put them, the one in trial of the other, will all be ready to helpe.</p>
            <p>We haue thoughte good that he
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:21658:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>ought to be choſen captain, that hath children, but for all that he ought not to be refuſed that hath none, ſo that otherwiſe he be ſtronge and prudent. If he haue children that be as yet but of tender yeares, they retayne altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther bounde the mynde of the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and as oſtages geuen to his cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, haue force to kindle in their father a marueylous fayth and beneuolence towardes it, &amp; as it were with ſharpe ſpurres to pricke him, and to inflame his minde againſt the enemies: and if hys children be nowe come to fuller age, with weapons, with fidelitie, with counſell, with diligence, accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paniyng him in the trauayles and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment, and faythfully ſeruinge in ſecret thinges, they may vnto a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon welth bringe muche profit.</p>
            <p>Why he ought to be a goodly ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, is for that of this, concerning the thinges that is to be entreated in the affayres of warre, we iudge there wyl followe muche vtilitie. Conſideringe that eyther hauynge occaſion to ſette men in araye to the battaile, the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine with faire wordes comfortinge the Souldiers, eaſelye may perſwade euery one of them to deſpiſe al perils,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:21658:11"/>and to attende to the glorious enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe: nor the ſounde of the trumpet, canne ſo muche inflame the mindes of men to take their weapons, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraine them moſt valiantly to faight, as the conuenyent, and accordinge to the time, the ſugred talke of the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine maye moue theym, bothe vnto great actes for the loue of vertue, and incorage them for the deſire of glorye, or ells if neede be, to comeforte the mindes afflicted for ſome ouerthrowe had, his wordes ſhalbe as a medicine. Wherfore, for the benefit of the Hoſt, for to lighten the heauineſſe of accy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentes, the Acomodate ſpeakinge of the Captaine, by moſt reaſon, is more to be deſired then the induſtrie of ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geons, which folow the campe, onelye to thende to heale woundes: for that they take no charge, but to cure the hurts: But he with ſwete and curteis maner of ſpeakinge, comforteth and moſte highly maketh glad the mindes of the weake and afflicted. Beſides al this, he confermeth the minds of them that be whole, and retaines them that be boldened. Then how much more difficulte it is to heale the infirmities that is hydde, then thoſe whiche maye
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:21658:12"/>be bothe felte and ſeene, euery manne knoweth. And like as no Citye will neuer make armye, nor ſende theym without a Captaine, and determined gouernement, euen ſo neyther oughte the Captaine to be choſen ſuch a one, that knoweth not, nor hath not the grace in ſpeakinge, and that lacketh the faceletie and vtteraunce of ſpeach.</p>
            <p>Laſt of all we ſaid that it behoueth to choſe the Captaine, that is eſtemed and of reputacion: for as muche as the common people, haue a cuſtome il wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linglye to ſuffer to be ſubiect to them who be of baſe condicion, &amp; that haue neuer gotten neither honor nor glory. And truly there is none, if by compul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion he be not made, that will be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to folow that Captaine, who he knoweth to be of leſſe worthines then himſelfe. Neceſſary it is therfore, that he be famous and noble, and by the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion of al men to be iudged valiant. And ſuch a man of vertue, of ſtomake, and of maners, as we aboue haue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared he ought to be.</p>
            <p>But as I holde oppinion, that no Captaine is to be elected, hauing any reſpect to riches: euen ſo I iudge the poore man is not to be refuſed, ſo that
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:21658:12"/>he be a good man, and a valiaunt. For in dede, I ſuppoſe not that any manne for the defaulte of fortune, whether he be poore or rich, deſerues eyther to be praiſed or diſpraiſed. And ſurely euery man that is of abillitie and riche, and beſides that adourned with bounti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe, ſo muche differeth from the pore, as an armor garneſhed with ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, and trimmed with gold, excelleth that which is made of iron and braſſe, and that lacketh ſuch kinde of ſettyng forth. And ſure it is, that the one and the other, may couer and lykewiſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fende the Souldier: but the one ſemes to be more excellente then the other, onelye for the giltinge and ornament that outward is adioyned.</p>
            <p>It is nedefull likewiſe, to haue ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertiſement not to choſe any, the whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che attends to gather money, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuallye hath his minde vpon luker, and altogether is ſubiect to gayne, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit he ſeme aboue all other neuer ſo aboundant and riche, as doeth euerye ſort of marchaunts, banckers and ſuch of lyke profeſſion: for as muche as ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily, they be death, and of litle ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke, as thoſe that with al their ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye attende to euery ſmall gayne, and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:21658:13"/>gyues themſelues in praye to money. Wherby it hapneth that there can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer growe in them, deſire of any ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable, illuſtreous, or noble enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe.</p>
            <p>Surely in a Captaine, I iudge that it is to be made accompte of, the repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacion and Nobilitie of hys predeceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, if that chaunce in him to he fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, but where no ſuch thinge is, it ought not to be greatly paſſed vpon: neyther for ſuch cauſe, no man is to be reputed worthy to gouerne. And as in horſe we will conſider their readines, and not that which appeareth outwardly, ſo I am of opinion, that iudgement is to be made of the nobilitye of men. It is verely, a fooliſh and ſtraunge thing not to conſider who &amp; what they be, vnto the which muſt be geuen commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to defende and to kepe oure Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate, and yet to beholde what they haue bene, and what their predeceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſours haue done: as if they which now ſo long agon are dead, might both de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fende and ſaue vs. Moreouer, it is a thinge altogether vniuſt, and that in no maner of wife is conuenient, by order or lawe of Armes, to determine, that to them, the whiche haue in ſome
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:21658:13"/>affaires acquited them ſelues valiant he geuen rewards and honors, not for being borne of moſt noble parentage: and to iudge afterwarde, that for a Captayne he ought to be choſen, the which only hath his originall of vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aunt and noble progenitours, and not he that doth truſt in his owne proper vertue, wherin he excelleth, although he lacke the glory and brauenes of his Aunceſtry and ſtocke. The which thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges ioined vnto vertue, ſuch a captain I ſuppoſe verelye, ſhoulde be ſo mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che the more aduenturous: but where lacketh his proper vertue, I eſteme him without any doubt, to be altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vaine and vnprofitable: yea, and by moſt reaſon it is to be thought, that they will become better Captaynes, the whyche of illuſtrious and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous bloud, cannot muche boaſte, for as muche as they, whome in the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thines of their forefathers, doe truſt, thinke for the ſelfe ſome renowme of theim, to be honoured, if ſometime in their offyce, they co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit any fault: ſuch confidence they haue in the reputaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and name of their Anſetry: wherby it hapneth, that oftentimes they more negligently gouerne. But theſe that
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:21658:14"/>haue no maner of hope in the glory of their Aunſeters, &amp; to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hath not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cended any ſparke of worthines, from their forefathers, whileſt w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> their own proper ſolicitatenes and induſtry, they deſire vnto the contrarye of their vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knownes, to put in light, their owne proper actes, more warelye they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure thinges, &amp; in the ende with more prompt and glad minde diſpoſe them ſelues to euery perill. And like as they that by inheritance haue not had lefte theim great aboundaunce, nor riche patrimonie, more circumſpectlye will kepe their goodes, then the richer or welthier wil do, for aſmuch as they with all diligence and labour, wil in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force theim ſelues to increaſe always: euen ſo thoſe, whiche can not ſerue them ſelues of the fame and glorye of their fathers, as a thing of inherita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce: by all maner of wayes, ſeke to attaine reputacion, whiche ſhall be of their owne proper indeuor.</p>
            <p>We ought therfore to choſe the cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, valiaunte, of noble bloude, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenturus, ryche, but yet neuertheles the poore is not to be deſpiſed and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed, ſo that he, althoughe he be not borne of illuſtrious progenitours be
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:21658:14"/>famous, and eſtemed, for his own pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per vertue. And after that he is elected and confirmed in ſuche degre, be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant, gentle, and chereful to them that will come to his preſence: notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandinge he ought not in euery place to euery man ſhew him ſelf ſo benigne and gentell: leaſt he happen to be deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſed, neyther ſo proude, and ſtoute, that he moue other to beare hym ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred. And that he doe this to thintent that with to muche licence and benig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitye, he cauſe not the Armye to be diſſolute, or with ſharpenes and ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, make them alianate theyr min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, and to become enemies.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>Of chuſynge the heades of the Souldiers.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Capytayne muſt elect and ordein the Decurians,
<note place="margin">A Decuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an is a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> captaine of ten men A Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turian is a captaine of a C. ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </note> the Centuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, and ordinatelye the other heades of Souldy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, accordynge as the thinge ſhall require, and as he ſhall
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:21658:15"/>thynke to be nedefull. And of theſe to take and choſe thoſe, whoſe vertue is wel knowen: and that be lykewiſe ſtronge and bolde, and faythfull to their countrie. And in makinge ſuche election, it makes no matter to take both noble &amp; rich, (for aſmuch as there is not to be choſen only, one or two) that amongeſt a fewe, and thoſe that be of good and honeſte maners, the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection may be the eaſier. When ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in diſtributinge with order, and laſtely the number of the Decurians, of the Centurians, and finallye of the other heades, the richeſt, and the moſt noble, are moſt nedeful. And ſurely it is of much vtility to a common welth to ſet forward y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> nobility at ſuch time when an enterpriſe is to be taken in hand, in the doyng wherof is required ſeleretie. Likewiſe alſo, the commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of money is greatlye to be deſired, when it is neceſſarye to geue ſome thing to the Souldiers, &amp; to ſpende li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berallye. For that the liberalitie of Princes and leaders, althoughe it be but a litle, if with benignitie, liberal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and at time conuentent, it be vſed, it may get moſte great beneuolence of the multitude: and from thenceforth the moſt aſſured fidelitie of the Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:21658:15"/>gotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, it doth ad vnto it ſecurety and conſtantenes in the enterpriſe, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in dede euery man hopes to obtain greater thinges, bearinge them ſelues valiantlye in fayghtinge, whan they knowe that in litle thinges, the libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralitie of the Captaine co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth of the proper benignitye of his owne minde.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>Of Counſellers.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eſydes all thys, it is neceſſarye that the Captain haue with him ſome Counſellours and companions, with who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he may deliberate vpon euery matter. And they being made partakers of the counſelles, muſte in time and place tell their iudgementes. And let him choſe theym eyther before he purpoſe to do any thyng, that they may folow him, and the army for to doe their of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, or els after that he ſhalbe ſet for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, to cal before the day of battaile, of the moſt nobleſt, &amp; of greateſt gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitye, and to cauſe them to come vnto him, the whyche together wyth him, ought of euerye thynge to debate.
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:21658:16"/>For as much as al thoſe thinges, that anye man of hym ſelfe hath founde, he may alone by him ſelfe with ſtudy examine, but he oughte not ſtrayght wayes to approue and confirme it: for that our thoughts and Councels, as a thing vnto the which we haue a natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, if of others faythful cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſel it be not holpen, eaſely it may beguile vs, and many times it is founde to be full of errorres: contrarywyſe, thoſe thinges, that by iudgement and opy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of other be aproued, dothe aſſure the mynde, and kepeth thynges ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and ſure. Notwithſtanding, no man oughte ſo little to truſte on hym ſelfe, that alwayes he be of opinyon weake and doubtfull, nor of him ſelfe ſo much to preſume, that he thinke o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther cannot fynd councell better then his. For that it ſhalbe neceſſary, that he, whiche is alwayes ſubiecte to the councell of other, hauing altogether diſtruſte of him ſelfe, come to chaunge infinite thinges, wherby in waightye matters, both hurt &amp; incomoditie doth folowe, as lykewyſe he muſt nedes, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther alwayes or often tymes commit errorre, that not hearing the aduiſe of other, euerye thinge doth atribute to
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:21658:16"/>him ſelfe alone.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>Of the warre that is to be taken in hande.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Iudge that the warre ought to be begun cyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſpectly &amp; with pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, as a ſure founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of thinges, wherby to all menne, may as it were moſte clearely appeare, to be for good cauſe taken in hande. That for the ſame they may hope that God wil be gracious and fanourable. And then, the ſouldiers with boldnes more gladlier and more redier will go whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſo euer thou liſte to execute thy commaundementes: as they the whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che doth well knowe, that they ought to do iniurye to no man of their owne wil &amp; deſire, but when they are prouo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked and conſtrayned, to take them to their Armor. For the whiche thing with al their force, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> ſtomackes, they wyll <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> forwarde <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> haue to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, thoſe that thinke peraduenture vniuſtly to haue begonne the warre, will haue ſuſpitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:21658:17"/>that god wilbe againſt them diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and contrary, for which only opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> although there happen not any thing vnfortunatelye, yet they will ſtande with feare and terrorre. Wherefore vnto a Captaine it is conuenient that of thoſe thinges, the whiche he eyther requireth, or beinge of other requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that he do not graunt theym, firſt by mouth, and afterwarde by waye of Ambaſſadours to intreate thereof: to thintent that eyther demaunding iuſt thinges, or denying the vniuſt, he may ſeme to be prouoked to riſe in armes. Finally it is good to cal to witnes god and men, that he hath not vndertaken to make warre for deſpite, and vnad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſedlye, as though to him there could not happen thoſe thinges, which often tymes are wonte to chaunce to them, that make warre: nor alſo for that he for an obſtinate mynde couereth to do harms and to ruinate the people. And in dede where not onelye in the buyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge of houſes and walles, it is mete to caſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> foundation, to the ende <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> weake beginninges, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> thou <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                  <desc>••…</desc>
               </gap>ſt edefie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, wyſe wyth muche more dilygence
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:21658:17"/>and aduertiſement, greater ſurenes, &amp; eſtabliſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, is to be vſed in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings of warre, before men be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>duc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted abrode, &amp; an Armie leuied. For as muche as the weake beginninges of thinges, cannot ſuſtain y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> waight that is laide vpon them, but eaſely oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, &amp; of euery accedent beate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, they wil fall, &amp; altogether go to ruin. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is nedefull to take inſample by the ſkilfull maiſter of the ſhippe, who before he go out of the hauen to enter into the ſea, doth furniſhe the ſhip, of all manner of thynges neceſſarye, and as much as he can poſſible, doth arme and decke it, &amp; afterwardes ſettes him ſelfe to ſailing. Becaufe it is a thing reprochfull and perilous, to make a ſhew of mouing warre after ſuch ſort, for which by ſea and by land, men are conducted, and afterward in a mome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in the preparation thereof to ſtay, and in the middeſt of the courſe, &amp; alſo in the force it ſelfe, to turne (as the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſaiyng is) the taile, and moſt ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mefully to retire, or els foliſhly to put in peril the ſtate of al things, &amp; to be of euery man mocked, not only for light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, but alſo being deſpiſed, for that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people will repute thee of ſmall wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thines, thou ſhalt be eſteamed ſubiect
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:21658:18"/>to al kinde of iniury. After which wil folow y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thy enemyes (albeit they haue not ſuffred any harme, thou minding to haue hurt theym, but hauing not bene able, both for vilenes, and for lacke of wiſedome) wyll beare vnto thee, cruell and mortall hatred.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>Of conducting foorth the Army</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Auing firſt pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged euery publike blot &amp; faulte, and made cleane euery priuat error &amp; vici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes, &amp; ſuch purgation of ſinnes being done with praiers and ſacrifices, as by way of religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly law hath co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded, or as it is or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deined of the prieſts themſelfes, the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my may then be conducted out, which alwayes muſt be led in battel ray, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it haue not as yet to come to the ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds with thenemies: &amp; in like ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner when it hathe occaſion to paſſe through Countreis which are of le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth many daies iorney, albeit that they be quiet and peaſable. For as much as, after this ſorte, the ſouldiers will ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtome them ſelues to obſerue the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ray, &amp; ſpecially euery man will learne to ſtand in his place, &amp; to follow theyr leaders &amp; Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtables. The which thing
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:21658:18"/>much more carefully muſt be obſerued when it ſhall be neceſſarye to marche through the dominions of the enemy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, to the end that by ſodaine aſſaults, thy ſouldiers be not conſtrained at e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery ſtep, to riſe in a rumor, and confu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſedlye to run here and there; &amp; the one to go contrary to the other, and finally coming about thee, in diuers maners, not to be able to do any thing of anye profite. For which cauſe, through eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry place, thou oughteſt to march with the army in battaile ray, whereby the ſouldiers may be made more apt and ſpedy to make a voyage, &amp; quicke &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to reſiſt if nede ſhalbe: they hauing learned to folow y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> anſignes, to attend to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, &amp; to behaue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelfes valiantly, according to theyr place &amp; order. If thou lead thy army by ſuche places, thou oughteſt to bring the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cloſe together, &amp; retire them in litle ſpace, ſo that by the ſtraightnes, &amp; by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> faci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litye of inlarging, thou be not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to extende thy ſelfe into too much length. Which faſhio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of marching ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes to geue power to the ennemye, to aſſault co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modiouſly their aduerſaries &amp; according to the occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to hurt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, he knowing to be taken fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them the commoditie to defend their ſelues.
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:21658:19"/>For aſmuch as, either with more large order, coming againſt thee, the which is wont to hapen (both the hornes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing compaſſed) it is like that he ſhall eaſly diſorder thee, &amp; put the to flight: or els geuing y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> charge on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> flank, in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> midſt of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſquadro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, haui<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g alredy broke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> order, ſodenly ſtop thy men from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing able to go forward, being cloſed in the arays of theyr enemies. Wherfore minding to retire into a main battel, &amp; to turne to reſiſt, they ſhalbe able to do litle good, as thoſe that haue vſed ſuch a maine battel, which for hauing not any thickenes, is nothing ſtrong, but rather altogether weake. Finally if the enemy geue the aſſault behinde on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> laſt bande, thou ſhalt be brought to the very ſame neceſſitye, after ſuch ſort, that not onlye it ſhalbe ſeen that he may be able to take awaye the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer to reſiſt, but alſo be able to geue thee moſt manifeſt ouerthrowe. But yf thou tourning backward, haue ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke to faight, thou ſhal be oppreſſed of the ſelfe ſame difficulty, whiche we ſhewed, might be impedime<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to them that be placed in the front, for as mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che as thou mayſt be ſodenly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſſed about and taken. Moreouer, it is wont to happen whileſt the thing goeth not
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:21658:19"/>euen, that thou canſt not eaſelye geue ſuccour to that part of thy men which are beaten and wery. For aſmuch as if thou call the firſt, to ſuccour the laſt, or els contrariwiſe cal the laſt to geue helpe to them that be in the fronte, it ſemes that theſame, vncomodiouſly, &amp; to late, may be brought to effect, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing nede both to theſe, and to thoſe, to run vp and downe by a long ſpace, and diſtaunce of ground. For the whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che thing, it is alwayes better, and more ſure, and more eaſye to gouerne the bandes that march cloſe &amp; ſquare, then thin and long: ineſpecially for as much as, to an armye that marcheth with the bandes long, often times is wont to happen, that of ſomthing ſeen doubtful &amp; vncertaine, there groweth ſodenly feare and terror. Becauſe ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time it hath chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſed, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> men decending from high places &amp; hilly, in the plain, to places expedite &amp; open, &amp; the formoſt ſeing the laſt of the ſelfe ſame band, by a very great diſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to come after, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing them ſelues to be aſſauted of ſome ambuſhe of enemies, it hath ben ſene that they haue ſodenly turned to faight, and afterwardes: no otherwiſe then as with enemies, haue with their owne fellowes gone together by the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:21658:20"/>eares. The victuailes, the caryages, &amp; al the remnant of prouiſion of thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrumentes of war, I iudge ſhould be placed in the midſt of the army: except the places that are left behinde, be ſo ſafe, that without daunger ſuch thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges may be caried and conducted af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the army: but if it ſhall be other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, the hindemoſt part wold be gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded &amp; defended of the moſt valiant ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, as alſo is to be don in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> formoſt becauſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vnawares may happe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> many thinges. Likewiſe there ought to be ſent afore, certain men on horſbacke, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which ſhould go inueſtigating, &amp; ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing where they may paſſe, ineſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hauing occaſion to make voyages by mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tains, by woods, by places in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hils, &amp; by moſt great deſerts. Becauſe that many rymes, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> enemye hauing oportunity to laye an ambuſh priuſly by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> paſſage, &amp; to aſſault his ad<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uerſaries, which litle therof toke hede hath eaſily broken &amp; altogether ruina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted them. The which ambuſhes if our Captaine by way of explorators ſhall forſee, with a litle paine hauing pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uented y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> councel of the enemy, he may attain a moſt great name of prudence and likewiſe ſaue his army. But the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen plaines, which becauſe they may
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:21658:20"/>be eſely ſene without ſending afore a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſpy, thou with thine own eies, may take hede. For as much as in the day, duſt moued and lifted vp in the ayre, doeth ſhewe the ſtirring of ennemies, and in the night, the fires &amp; the flame, ſignifieth their campe to be neare.</p>
            <p>When thy men are to be conducted to make a voyage, &amp; not for to faight, thou oughteſt to remoue by day, if per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ture ſome thing do not conſtraine thee, for the which thou thinkeſt good to go in haſt, to come before thenemy, where in dede for ſuch occaſion, thou maieſt remoue by night, ſo that thou know, that ſafelye it may be done.</p>
            <p>Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou comeſt in place where thou art conſtrained ſtraight way to come to the handes with thy enemy, and to faight, lead thy men not in haſte, but ſoftly, &amp; inforce theim not to make to long a iorney: foraſmuche as, labour taken before men come to faight, is ſene moſt often times, vainely to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume the force and ſtrengthe of their bodies. But yf thou muſte marche wyth thy menne in the Countrye of thy fryendes, it is nedefull that thou commaund thy Souldiers, that in no maner of wyſe, they touche or marre any thing, but rather altogether to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frayne:
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:21658:21"/>conſyderyng that Souldiers truſtyng in their weapons, &amp; hauing liberty to do what ſhall pleaſe them, wyll fauour nothyng; ineſpecially for that the ſighte of thinges that pleaſe men, out of doubt are wont moſt dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerouſly to leade ignoraunt, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wareful men, to deſire them, and with the ſweteneſſe of robbing, to entice them to do al maner of miſchiefe.</p>
            <p>Whereunto yf thou prouydeſt not, thy frendes and confederates, for eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſmal occaſion wil become enemies. Notwythſtandyng, the country of thy aduerſaryes, thou ſhalt ſuffer thy ſoul diers ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly to ruinate, deſtroy, burne, and conſume, becauſe by the dearth of victualles, and lack of money, warres are wonte to diminyſhe, and to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſhed: and contrariwiſe, through abundance and riches, they are nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed and maintained.</p>
            <p>But firſte before thou ſuffereſt thy enemies countrie to be deſtroyed, thou ſhouldeſt geue aduice to thy enemies, threatning them, what thou wilte do, yf they wil not yelde vnto thee: for that the perill of the miſery prepared, and the feare of the ruine loked for, of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten tymes conſtraines men to graunt many thinges, the whiche at the firſt,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:21658:21"/>by no maner of meane had bene poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to haue brought them to do.</p>
            <p>But after that they haue once re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued the hurte, they will make litle accompte of thee, and deſpyſe al other thynges, as though thou couldeſt doe them no more harme.</p>
            <p>Albeit, if thou knoweſt ſurely, that in the countrey of thy ennemies, thou muſt tary lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g with thy army, ſuffer to be taken, &amp; ſpoiled only thoſe things, which thou ſeeſt not to be greatly prs<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fitable vnto thee: but the ſame which is to be thought, may be preſerued for thy commodity, commaund openly vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to thy Souldiers, that they forbeare.</p>
            <p>Hauyng made readye, and ſette in order thy men, tarrye not long in thy owne countrye, nor yet in the ſame of thy confiderates: leſt that conſuming al thy prouiſion, it ſeme not that thou be of greater hurt to thy frendes, then to thy ennemyes: but rather conducte quickly thine army, into the aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries countrey, wherby if it be fertyle &amp; abundant, there may be taken at thy nede, moſt plenteouſlye thoſe thinges that thou liſt. But if it be otherwiſe, thou ſhalt cauſe to be knowen, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſekeſt to prouyde moſt louinglie, both for the wealth &amp; profit of thy frendes.
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:21658:22"/>And where the Countrey of the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies is fertyle, and aboundaunt, there may be taken thereof much commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye, and great profite.</p>
            <p>Beſides this, thou oughteſt to care wyth all diligence, that in thy campe, both by Sea, and Land, victuall maye be ſafelye broughte, for aſmuche as by ſuche meanes, the Marchauntes will endeuour wyth all dilygence, to bring all thoſe thinges, which for the vſe of an Army ſhalbe neceſſarye.</p>
            <p>Moreouer, when thou muſt paſſe throughe ſtraight places, or muſte cauſe the Armye to marche throughe rough and hilly wayes, then it is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient principallye for the preſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of thy things, to ſend before ſome to take and keepe the higheſt places, the rockes, the foordes, and other encloſed wayes, to thende, leaſte the enemyes goinge before thee, come not to take them, and ſo eaſelye to keepe the paſſage from thee. The contrarye thou oughteſt to enforce thy ſelf to do, when thou vnderſtandeſt that thy ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mye muſt paſſe through ſuch roughe, &amp; ſtraight places. Seing that not only, thou haſt to take hede not to receiue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny harme, but alſo to enforce thy ſelfe to turne againſt the enemye the verye
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:21658:22"/>ſame deceites, whereby he thinkes to deceiue thee withal. And like as when thou purpoſeſt to go againſt him, it is requiſite to ſolicitate the matter, to be able to be afore him, and at vnawares to oppreſſe hym, euen ſo with all dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence, thou oughteſt to prouide to let him euery way, if thou vnderſtandeſt that he entendes to come againſt thee.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>Of lying in the field.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hy tentes being pitched in the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>try of the enemies, althoughe thou haue not delybe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated longe to tarye in the ſame place, yet there muſt be out of hand made the diches &amp; the tre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ch. For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſmuche as after this ſort, thou ſhalte ſtand more fortefied. Whereby the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine inuaſions and craftye aſſaultes of the enemyes, maye more ſafelye be withſtode.</p>
            <p>And moreouer, thou maiſt chuſe ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, to whom charge muſt be geuen, that night and day, they kepe watch &amp; warde in the Campe, albeit that it be knowen that the enemye be farre of.</p>
            <p>But if thou be not letted of the enemyes: and purpoſeſt longer in the
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:21658:23"/>ſame place to kepe the Campe, eyther to geue the ſpoile to their Countrey, or to watche a more comodious oportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netie, to take occaſion to hurte them, then chuſe thoſe places where thou in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendeſt to pitche the campe, that it be not durty, nor through other ocaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bolſome, for that the nature &amp; the ſitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation of ſuche places, through the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt vapours, and through the ſtinke that they ſende forth, diuers infirmy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and peſtilence, is wont to be indu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ced, and ingendred: whereby who ſo e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer is infected, is greuouſly afflicted, and manye maye happen to dye, after ſuch ſort, that dying alwayes a greate ſort, not only euery day the Army wil diminiſh, but alſo through the debeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty &amp; melancoly which they haue, that remaine aliue, they wil fall ſick &amp; lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh beyond meaſure.</p>
            <p>And therefore holeſome and profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble it is, not to kepe the armye to long in one place. Excepte it be that thou arte conſtrayned to remayne, for oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to winter, and to aunyde the colde and the ſharpenes of the ayre. Furthermore, moſte greate care is to be hadde, that the Tentes and the Pauilions, be pitched in order, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſuche ſorte, that thou maiſte bee
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:21658:23"/>thought to inhabits a place lyke vnto a litle Citye. Foraſmuch as other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyſe, the euacuaſions of bodyes, that long is made in one place, ſende forth corrupte vapours, the contagiouſneſſe of whiche diſperſed, cometh to infecte the ayre nere about, and lightly tour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth it, into a naughtie vnholeſome qualitie, by whiche continuall vſe, and neceſſary cuſtome, we take diuers and perilous infirmities.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>Of exerciſynge the Souldiers.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen the Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyers in the wynter be at home, they ought to be excerciſed, &amp; with di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers maſteris be made apte to fayght: ſo that neyther ydlenes nor ſluggiſhnes, haue at no tyme any place. Surely the ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in ydlenes &amp; in ſlugguiſhnes, ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>keth the bodies to become weake and languiſhed, and it yeldes the mindes altogether vile and feareful. For that alſo the mindes of them, that be moſte
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:21658:24"/>ſtoute, do therby become feble, whileſt they be taken by the flattery of plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, &amp; of continual vſe of delicatnes. For whiche thing, menne ought not much to abſent them ſelues from acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uity, &amp; from laboure: Becauſe, if after idlenes thou wouldeſt conſtraine anye to labour, they wyl not go to the ſame very willingly, and going, they will not continue, as thoſe which inured w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> long ſlothfulnes, feare labour, and flie euery ſafe enterpriſe, not as yet made, and finally if to any place, they wil go to attempt ſome act, ſodainly they wil depart, &amp; altogether diſtruſting the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, cannot &amp; will not ſuſtain labour. And therfore it is the offyce of a wyſe Captaine, to ordaine quietly, &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diouſly to make ready thoſe thinges, which he knoweth to be profitable for theym, whileſt he is not compelled of any neceſſity to faight, &amp; whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it ſemes that they ſtand in no maner of perill, nor anye impediment happen theym that maye let him to comaunde hys ſouldiers, to do thoſe things for the ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>erciſe of their bodies, which the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is not nedefull to ſerue againſt the ennemy. Finally, euery thing without perill that is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted to the ſouldiers to do, as the ſame that inſtructeth, teacheth &amp;
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:21658:24"/>maketh them apt to the true maner of faighting, may ſeme to haue many co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient diſports, &amp; recreations, yea &amp; to them which with wearines be greued.</p>
            <p>Souldiers be kept in exerciſe, in this maner: let ſome of them be choſen, &amp; to euerye one be geuen the weapons, for ſuche a thing conuenient, &amp; armed, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtome them to keepe the order, and learne neuer to forſake their owne place, &amp; beſides that, with taking hede the one to the other, &amp; calling them of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, &amp; with familiar practiſe together to vnite &amp; to draw together the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues, after ſuch ſorte, that euery man maye learne &amp; know in what place &amp; ranke, euery one is placed, &amp; to ſtande ready to obey without delay, their captaines co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundementes. Beſides this, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers according as they ſhalbe taught, muſt be inſtructed in knowing how to deſtend &amp; bring together the bandes, &amp; on the right hand, &amp; on the left hande, to turne them. Make them learne alſo according to the order, the tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſferring of the ſqadro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from place to place, &amp; the mouing the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues without confuſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; the way to inlarge &amp; draw together y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> rankes, &amp; finally the going forth, &amp; the returning nowe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> one, now the other,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:21658:25"/>and the deuiſions and compartiments made by the Decurians: &amp; the maner alſo to ingroſe the ba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds in largenes, &amp; to extend them in length, &amp; to faight, of the one ſide, and of the other, with battel deuided in .ii. partes, ineſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally when the laſt and reſcuing ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, tourning theym about, do reſiſt the ennemyes, who ſeeke to compaſſe them. Laſte of all, it is needefull, to admonyſhe the ſouldiers, that they ſtande attentyue to vnderſtande the ſignes, which by commaundement of the Captaine, ſhal be geuen whileſt they faight: and whan the Trompette ſoundes to retire, that with good or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der they doe gather together, and a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle and a litle, withdrawe them from the batraile. And verily to them, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che beginne to indeuour theym ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues to learne muſicke, it is wont to chaunce, that at the firſte where they ſhoulde ſet their fingers in the holes of the inſtrumentes of flutes, or in the ſtops of inſtrumentes with ſtringes, they ſet them cleane contrary, and vſe them without arte, ſo that they make no Armonie: and lykewyſe ſcant extend them, and ſlowly moue them. But they that by practiſe, exerciſe and
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:21658:25"/>reaſon, be expert in ſuch ſcience, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any paine, eyther when it is nede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to gyue a little or muche winde, or els with the finger to ſtop the ſtrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, conueniently, &amp; wyth commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye, geue and withholde the breath, &amp; with meaſure and quicknes moue the hande, heretofore accuſtomed.</p>
            <p>The very ſame happeneth to theym that be rude, and that hath not the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience of the feares of warre. In the begining it ſemes that with trauaile and difficultie, through manye errors and long ſpace of time it is before they maye be inſtructed and kept in battel raye. But ſo ſone as they be taught and made perfecte, of them ſelues they will ſette them to the place, vnto the order, &amp; to the thing that they haue to do, euery one of them wonderfully in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forſinge them accordinge to their po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, to make a faire and in al pointes a well ordered muſter.</p>
            <p>The Armye beinge learned and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deined after this maner: I woulde de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide them in two partes, &amp; then with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out weapon bring them cloſe together to fayght, diſtributinge the light dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, and the ſlite parteſans: and if par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduenture there ſhalbe nere ſome plo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:21658:26"/>fielde, lette theym faight wyth the cloddes of earth, and let the ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers vſe harnes of Bulles lether, yf they may haue it. But if there were litle hilles or places, ſomwhat rough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er then plaine, and lykewiſe pendent, by commaundement of the Captaine, let there be appointed one parte of Souldiers, to euerye one of which, let there be geuen ſuch ſort of weapon as is mete, and geuynge theim ſelues to run, take thoſe plates: and to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, let there be choſen of the other, to whome be geuen charge, that with like weapons they inforce them ſelues from ſuch places to driue away thoſe, that kepe the highe grounde, and to enter their ſelues. Finally, the fayght finiſhed, let the Captaine praiſe thoſe the which without euer being moued, haue their places to them appointed, euen to the laſte defended: or els to praiſe them which hauing driue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> away the other, haue entred their ſelues. With this maner of faighting, final<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with this emulacion, and with this diligence, the army is conſerued, and the bodies of ſouldiers purged, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhed after ſuche ſort, that euery one of them willingly wil vſe euery ſorte
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:21658:26"/>of meates, and ſwetelye take euerye drinkinge, not caringe, anye further, to ſeeke thinges neither greatly fine, or delicate, nor muche exquiſite. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bunger the which comes v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon men throughe the trauaile of la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, and the drines that commeth to them that through labouring ſwete, howe ſymple ſo euer the meate and drinke be, it wilbe thought to be a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licate diſhe, and a ſweete drinkinge. Whereby the bodies of Souldiers be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come more luſty and nimble. For that thoſe which be wont to labor in heate and cold in the open aire, as men glad and readye, do ſubmit them ſelues to trauell, and alſo luſtely ſuſtayne it.</p>
            <p>In the very ſame maner, ſhoulde be exerciſed the horſmen. In the preſence of the Capytaine to be ordeined the running in triall the one of the other, the purſuing after, the flyinge, the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countringe, the charginge of their ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, ſpeciallye in places playne and large, or els at the foot of hilles, as far as the borſes may go for the ſtepe and ſtony places: for in deede they ought not to be inforced to runne there, where it is to highe and pending, or to muche ſtepe and downeright.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="44" facs="tcp:21658:27"/>
            <head>Of makyng the ſpoyle.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE ſpoyle ought moderatelye to be made, and it is not to be borne withall, that the Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers be ſuffered preſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuouſlye to goe to rauin and to ſpoyle: nor to lette them goe to much wandering, in the Countrey of the enemyes, ineſpecially if it be riche and aboundaunte, bycauſe by ſuch ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, often tymes moſt great hurtes hath bene ſene to inſue. Where the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy findinge ſuche occaſion, and ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in order his people, aſſaulting the Souldiers diſordered and ſtrag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled for the ſweeteneſſe of the praye, or els of the ſame laden and let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, hath eaſely bene of power to put them to flighte, &amp; to breake and to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe them, they being not able com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modiouſlye to vſe their weapons, nor to geue ſuccour the one to the other. For whiche thing, thoſe that without commiſſion of the Captaine, do geue them ſelues to ſpoyle diſperſed, lette them be puniſhed with moſt greuous
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:21658:27"/>puniſhment, and ſhamed with notable reproche of infamye.</p>
            <p>But when thou determineſt to ſend of thy men to get booties, thou muſt togethers with thoſe that ſhal go diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>armed, ſende alſo horſemen and foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men expert and valiant, whom maye not a whit be occupied in the praye, but ſtanding continually in araye, be alwayes ready to ſuccor the ſpoylers, after ſuch ſort, that ſafely out of dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger they may returne.</p>
            <p>And if peraue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ture ſomtime thy ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies ſpies happen to be taken, thou muſt not vſe towardes them all, one maner of ſentence. If thou knowe cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly, that thy men, and all thy pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration, be leſſe then the ſame of thy enemy, then commaund that ſtraight way they may be killed. But if thy ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mye of men be of a great multitude, &amp; of weapons better furniſhed, and ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers more valtaunt, and more obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, and hauing leaders more expert, and more famous, then all thy Hoſte being ſet in good order, and as it were to muſter, commaunde that the ſpyes be led throughe out all, and that they haue libertie to beholde euerye thing
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:21658:28"/>diligently, and in thende, let them de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parte without anye maner of puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: for that they, reporting the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency of thy thinges, the puiſaunce and greate number of people, eaſelye will put in feare the enemies: like as the ſcarſitie of thinges, and dearth, is wont to bolden &amp; to geue them hope.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>Of watch and warde by night.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the tyme of nyght, there ought to be ordeined many watche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men: of the whiche, ſome muſt watch, and ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be apointed in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces for the wardes, &amp; the houres of the night deuided, the one after the other, may ſlepe &amp; repoſe them ſelues: for as muche as the ſouldiers ſhould not be conſtrained to make their warde wat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chinge, more then that whiche nature is able to ſuſtain, although they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe to ſtande in watche al the night. Where ſurely y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſweetnes of ſlepe, may cauſe a man to forget him ſelf againſt his will, and not to haue any care for his owne perſon, nature it ſelfe, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentinge
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:21658:28"/>therunto. Therefore, let eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man ſtande on his feete to watche: for as muche as, ſitting ſtretched out, doth take a waye a little and a litle, the ſtrengthe, and maketh weake and languiſheth the body, wherby the ſlepe lightly ouercomes. On the contrarye, the ſtandinge vpright and on the fete, kepeth the minde otherwiſe wakeful.</p>
            <p>Thoſe, whiche ſhalbe appointed to make the ward, let them go before the Campe, or els ſomewhat farther of, and make fyres after ſuche ſorte, that they maye ſee thoſe farre of, whiche peraduenture ſhal go in thoſe partes, where the fier ſhyneth, and of whome they can not be ſene, being ſet in dark places, and hauinge the light againſt them: by whiche way the enemies vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>awares maye come to the handes of the watche.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>Of remouing the Armye ſecretely.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>F at anye tyme thou haue determined to moue the campe ſecretly ſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> the enemies ſhal not
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:21658:29"/>knowe it, thou hauing neede to take ſome place, or els ſome of thine being taken in goinge to defende the ſame, or finallye to auoide the neceſſitye to come to the deede of Armes, fyrſte of all, commaunde that there be kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dled, moſt great fyres, and after cauſe the armie to remoue. For aſmuche as the fyres beinge ſeene, the ennemies thinkinge that thou reniemayneſt ſtil in the accuſtomed place, wil be ſtill and quiet. But if the fyres goe oute in the darknes of the night, and thou make thee ready to depart, the enne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies ſuſpecting that thou prepareſt to fly, will vſe diligence and ſpede, to let thee the paſſage, &amp; layinge Ambuſhes according to the occaſion, moſt ſharp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye will purſue thee.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>Of coming to communicacion with the Captaine of thenemies.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F it happen that thou muſte come to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munycacyon wyth the Captayne of the ennemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es hoſte, and wyth hym, (as oftentimes happeneth) to intreate
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:21658:29"/>of ſome matter, thou ſhalt take with thee the valianteſt &amp; moſt noble men of thine Armye, the whiche be in the flower of their age, tall and luſty, and of goodly perſonage, &amp; be alſo of faire and bright armour furniſhed. Becauſe many times it chaunceth, that the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy by ſeinge of ſuche men as com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth with the Captaine, hath iudged the remnaunt accordingly. And euery manne ſhalbe ſooner moued and dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen of thoſe things that he hath ſene, then of thoſe whiche by report he hath vnderſtode.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>Of Fugetiues.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>F peraduenture, any fugetiues, from the Campe of thenemies, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſcaped ſhal come in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thine, for to geue thee aduyſe of their power, or els of ſome counſell, or if they ſhall offer to guide thee, to thend that thou mayſt aſſault thy enemyes at vnawares, cauſe that they be kept in cuſtodye, ſo that they may vnderſtande to haue no libertye
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:21658:30"/>to goe where they liſte: but rather let it be to them manifeſt, that if thou tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtyng vpon them, with thy army ſhall ſafely obtain y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> victory: they ſhal haue for their rewardes moſt great plentye of gyftes, and moſt gentely being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated, ſhall go free where they wil. But if it ſhall be perceaued that deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berately they be come to betraye thy Army with deceipt, make them know that in the ſelf ſame peril of the thing, without any doubt they ſhall haue to end their lifes. And it is not to geue credit otherwiſe to fugetiues, but whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they know that they be not maſters of themſelues, but thou the whiche in their counſels aſſured doeſt ſee thy ſelfe, mayſt do therafter.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>Of conſidering the campe of the enemies.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He wyſe Capy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine ought with al di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lygence, to vew the Campe of the enemies: nor with leſſe forſeinge
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:21658:30"/>he hath to conſider the ſituation of the ſame. For aſmuch as, if ſomtime it be pitched in the plaine, in a rounde fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion, we oughte not for all that to thinke, that therein be but fewe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are ſhut vp in a litle circuit of grounde, for that the circular fy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure, is wonte to ſeme leſſe in behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding it, then with the minde maye be comprehended by proportioning the meaſure of a maſſiue thing. Likewiſe the largenes, the whych is drawen in compaſſe, is in effect of more capacity, then anye man beholding it, is able to iudge. To the contrary, if the ſides of the diſtaunce do extend in length, and in ſome place eyther crooked, or els in manye angles tourned, doeth incloſe vp, you haue not for that cauſe to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, that therein be great multitude of men, ſeinge that ſuche facion of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>campinge, ſheweth a certaine reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blaunce of greatneſſe, and notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandinge, doeth not containe in it ſo manie menne as might be within a ſpace made circularwiſe. But the campes lying vppon mountaines and hils, if in al places, they be not cloſed &amp; ioyned together, they may ſeme big<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, then yf they were in the playne,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:21658:31"/>and yet contayne leſſe number of men, then that whiche ſome man on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye beholdinge may throughly iudge. For as muche as they do leue manye places void &amp; forſaken: as thoſe places be, that haue ſome partes ful of diches and caues, or els roughe and ſtonye, wherby they be deſart, and of no man may be in any maner of wiſe inhaby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. But of neceſſitye it hapneth that the Campes are alwaies made after ſuch maner, and the diſtaunce in lyke length are extended, accordinge to the nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber of people. Wherfore when thou ſeeſt the Campe of the ennemies, ſhut vp in a litle circuite, hauing conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the place, and of the facion, do not eſteme it a litle, but being deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended in lengthe, let it not make thee afraid: for as much as this aforeſayde knowen, truſte thou in the aduertiſmen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of war, and when occaſyon ſerues, attempt to execute ſome high and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpriſe.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="53" facs="tcp:21658:31"/>
            <head>Of incamping.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Han thou muſte incampe thee, it is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite that thou bring together thy men, and in a litle ſpace of grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to drawe theym toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. If the enemies do prouoke thee, take hede not to conduct them foorth, but rather moſt cloſely retayne with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the trenche thy Souldiers cloſe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, after ſuche ſorte, that it ſeme, that which thou doeſt, to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtrained of feare. For as much as, many times the enemy, whiche lacketh experience of thinges, conſidereth not the facte, with that prudence, as is conuenient in the affaires of warre: but hauinge one onelye time, dued the Campe, and finally eſteaminge the aduerſari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es to be but fewe, and they for beinge afraide to refuſe altogether to faight, he beginneth to make of theym litle counte, and to ſtand negligently, and in the end being come oute of his lod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gings, and out of his fortification, go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth euery where without any hede ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:21658:32"/>as thoughe that no man were able to incountre him.</p>
            <p>Then he hauing occaſion to aſſault the enemy in his lodgings, boldly go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to beſege him, not coſidering what great nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber of men may iſſue out. For y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which confidence waxing proude, as though no thing contrary might hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him, he becometh altogether ſloth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and retcheleſſe, hauing not anye maner of care of chaunces to come.</p>
            <p>The which occaſion if thou determin prudently to rake, thy men being put in order, and they in a ſodaine takyng vppe a moſt great crie, thou ſhalt ſend them furthe, by the backeſide of thy Campe, and by other diuers goyng foorthes, and in ſundrie maners, run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning on the backe of the enemy, thou mayeſt aſſaulte and faighte with him moſt valiantlye. And in dede, if wyth lyke policy and forcaſtinge, thou ſhalt know howe to guide thy men, lightly thou maiſt perceiue if y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> enemy be like for to vſe againſt thee, ſuche deceites. And not only thou oughteſt to knowe that which thou haſt to do againſt the enemy, but alſo that there come not v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon thee ſome co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary accident. For as
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:21658:32"/>much as, with thoſe wayes that thou maiſt beguile thenemy, with the very ſame, thou muſt beware, not to be deceiued. For the way of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding howe to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guile other men, may be vnto thee, a guide to be able eaſely for to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſtygate, yf they in thy preiudis, do worke any thing.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>How Councels are not to be diſcloſed.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F ſometyme ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther daye or night, thou determine to remoue thy Armie, or take ſome Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye, fortreſſe, or Caſtell, or els to get ſome paſſage, or for to do ſecretlye ſome other enterpriſe with celeritie, that the enemies knowe not therof, doe not diſcloſe to anye thy ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crete, nor reuele not where thou
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:21658:33"/>intendeſt to conduct thy men, neyther that whiche thou haſt to doe, ineſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, if it were not peraduenture, a profitable thinge, the communicating it with ſome of the principals. But whan thou arte ariued, where thou knoweſt that it is nedefull quicklye to come to the dedes, commaunde that, whiche euery man hath to doe accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge to the occaſion, and geue order and withoute anye delaye of time, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penlye admonyſhe the conducters, and ſouldiers, and ſhew them to what ende the thinge goeth: and afterward with all ſpede, goe forwarde with the enterpriſe. For ſurelye it is a token of a foolyſhe man, and vndiſcrete, raſhly to euery one to manifeſt his councell, and to no purpoſe to diſcloſe the ſecre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes vnto the multitude. For as muche as, the euil diſpoſed perſons, and thoſe that haue a naughty minde towardes the common weale, attende lyke occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, whiche when they maye take, they fly ſodenlie to the enemies, for to geue ſuche aduiſe, wherby they beleue to attaine rewardes and honors. Nor there hath neuer bene anie Army, but that out of the ſame, for many cauſes as well free men as ſeruauntes, hath
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:21658:33"/>paſſed to the campe of the ennemies, ſpecially when they vnderſtande that ſome ſecret, or matter of importaunce is intreated of, or els doe knowe that the time aprocheth, to come to handes to do the feates of armes.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>How that before the armie is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducted forth, Sacrifice ought to be done.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>Erely thou ough<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teſt not to conduct forthe men, nor put them in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ray to faight, if firſte ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordinge as cuſtome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires, thou haue not made the ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices: and therefore it is needefull, to haue the Aruſpici, &amp; the deuiners, the which ſhoulde folowe the Army. But it ſhoulde be verye well done, and a thing to be muche deſired, if thou thy ſelf couldeſt know the reaſon to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the interiors, &amp; to do the ſacrifice, with thoſe ceremonies, that is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite, ſo that thou thy ſelfe maye well
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:21658:34"/>&amp; conueniently forſee thy thinges, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſpecially, being able with facilety to haue knowledge thereof. But hauing done ſacrifice, if thou haue learned thy deſire, and ſhalte knowe that the holye thinges be fauourable to thee, with couragious mind, thou ſhouldeſt goe to thenterpriſe. For as muche as, the conducters will geue knowledge vnto the other, of all that whiche the holy things declare, and wil put them in good hope, and wyll geue theym good courage, when they ſhall vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande, that beinge guided by the will of the Gods immortall, goe to faight. For the whiche opinyon, the Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers altogether takinge hart, chereful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye vnto euery perill, wyll put theym ſelues, as they which haue hope to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the vyctorie, and al the ſignes, &amp; euery voyce, and euery thing diligent lye wyl obſerue. Whereby happeneth that this worthye C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>remonie of pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like ſacrifices, with peticions &amp; vowes maye maruelouſly comfort, and cauſe better hope to increaſe in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mindes of them, which priuately moued w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> feare of religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, be made ſorowful for things aduerſe and abhominable. But if per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduenture
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:21658:34"/>after offeryng of the oſte thy vowes happen not to be fulfylled, and the Sacrifices not to goe proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſlye: thou oughteſt to remaine in the ſelfe ſame place, and not to moue thee, althoughe that other occaſion ſeme to conſtrain thee neuer ſo much. For what thing maye happen thee woorſe, then thoſe that fortune, and the ſacrifices do ſhewe thee? ſo that if that whiche is to come, might luckely ſuccede, thou ſhouldeſt by ſacrificing, haue had it graunted thee. For y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che thing, cauſinge more oſtes to be kylled, in the ſelfe ſame daye, thou muſte ſacrifyce them, and renewe the ſacrifices done: for euery litle moment of tyme, is of great importaunce, and eaſelye may both hurte and helpe, ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther taking, or altogether leauing the commodious occaſion of thinges.</p>
            <p>Surelye to me it ſeemes, that the Arte of the Aruſpici, by meane of the beaſtes, and their interiours, by a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne manner ſhewed, and reaſon to conſider, geueth knowledge, and decla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>reth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mouings of the celeſtiall ſtars, &amp; their riſing vp, &amp; their going downe
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:21658:35"/>and finally the inclinations of the fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gures of the triangles of quadratures and of the meaſures. For as much as, ſome of their litle minutes, differe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, vertue, and way to deuine, in the very ſame daye, yea in the ſelfe ſame howre haue cauſed ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>times, that ſome haue obtained kingdoms, or els being van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſhed and taken, haue bene put in priſon. Seing then, that at a time it happeneth that to ſome, doing ſacry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, is ſhewed that concerning taking in hande the faight, the thing ſhall procede well, and yet after the faight hath folowed the conflicte and ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw: therfore I haue thought it ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarye to ſpeake ſomewhat of thys matter.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>How it is nedeful to haue knovv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of places.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eyng (as it apea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth manifeſtly) both ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny &amp; ſundry countries of the world &amp; the ſituaſion of places, and the facion
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:21658:35"/>of prouinces of the land, of diuers ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, it hapneth thereby, that for the moſt part, a man may ſtande in doubt, and knowe not howe to determine in what places the fieldes is beſte to be pitched, and howe to ſette the battail to faight. There be ſome ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that haue knowledge of their owne countrie, but of others, they be igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunt and nothing ſkilful. Wherby it chaunceth, that the enemies being di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaunt, the ſpace of a dayes iourney, and craftely faining to be afraide, and not to haue ſtomacke to abyde the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of the aduerſaries, and making as though they would fly, cauſeth the capitayn litle expert of things, to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſew him no otherwiſe but as if he fled in good earneſt, &amp; more boldly to mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt &amp; folow him in chaſe. But whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he hauinge bene drawen through the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of purſuinge, and by vaine hope to oppreſſe the enemy, doth ſee him ſelfe to be brought to difficulte paſſages, and into places incloſed with moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines, ſurely in the ende, he percea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth too late, to be compaſſed aboute with enemies on euery ſide, and as it were ſhut vp in a Cage, the higheſt places, the ſtraightes, and the wayes,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:21658:36"/>whereby myght haue been ſome paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage to flye being now poſſeſſed of the enemy. Then beholding all aboute howe he hath been mocked, and ſeing all his armie diſperſed to be by the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſary aſſaulted, doth know hym ſelf to be brought headling into extreame co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fuſion, being by the propertie of the place depriued for being able to faight or to withſtande. And for to auoyde the ſhame of yeldinge, eſtemeth to bee better, and a more worthy thyng to dye of famine: or els being conſtray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to ſubmit him ſelfe, geueth liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie vnto the enemies, to doe by hym whatſoeuer ſhalbe their pleaſure. For whiche thing, the retiring that the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy maketh whiche hath reſemblace of flying, is alwayes to be had in ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicion. Nor it ought not boldely to be folowed, but rather regarde ſhould be firſt had to the places, and theire na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture diligently conſidered.</p>
            <p>Therfore in conducting foorth the men of Armes, it is ſpecially to be conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that by the ſelfe ſame waye, that thou entereſt, the paſſage maye be ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for thee to returne, or els to leaue of to enter, if thy returne may be letted, or being entred to vſe meanes to bee
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:21658:36"/>able to come foorth. Whiche maye be done in this maner: if the moſt imine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and broken places and wayes in the toppes of the mountaynes, be kepte with thy ſoldiers, wherby the paſſage whyleſt the returne ſhalbe neadefull, maye be open to thee. Theſe thinges be ſayde, not onely to thintent that thou of councell may ercell the enne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my: but alſo, that with all diligence thou mayeſt ſeeke and forſee, not to be at vnawares of him oppreſſed. For as muche as a fayre thing it is, to knowe with pollicie how to oppreſſe the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, but it is good and neceſſary to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of being deceiued by him.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>¶ <hi>Hovve no litle accoumpte is to be made of him that hath brought aduiſes.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Ho ſo euer that ſhall require to come to ſpeake w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thee, to geue aduiſe of ſome thyng, whether he bee free or bonde, commynge by day or night, let him be ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly receiued
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:21658:37"/>and not only be brought into thy pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uilion: but alſo if peraduenture in the voyage he ſhall come to mete with the, or in what ſo euer maner whether it be either in time when thou takeſt reſt, or eateſt or waſheſt, let his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming neuer be prohibited. For as mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che as, in like matters, the delaying, &amp; taking away the commoditye of men for comming to ſpeake with thee, or hauing ſeruauntes to whom is lawe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to let them, whiche woulde come to ſpeake with thee, is no other, but to leaſe the occaſion of moſte greateſt importaunce, and is likewiſe loſſe of time, whiche is deareſt aboue al other thinges: and finallye by ſuche negly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence to no purpoſe, to put thy thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges in ruine. For vndoubtedly, where the Captaynes bee admonyſhed and taught by ſuche meſſengers, it bath bene ſene, that ſhortly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter they haue ben able, to come to do thinges, which haue bene thought to haue bene of moſt great helpe to the whole ſtate</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="65" facs="tcp:21658:37"/>
            <head>Of the time vvhen the Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers ought to eate their meate.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>F peraduenture thou muſt needes lodge thy menne ouer againſt the campe of thenemies, giue order, that the ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers in the breake of day, do eat their meate. For as muche as, if thou per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue that it is in thy libertie, to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble as ſhal pleaſe thee, and when thou liſt, to put theym in araye, and bringe them to faight, then according as ſhal be moſt commodious for thee, thou mayeſt commaund euery manne, that they eate meate. But if thou happen to be brought to ſuche extremity, that eyther throughe the ſituacion of the place, or through the weakenes of the trenches and diches, or els for ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther cauſe, wherby it lieth in adbetri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the enemies to inforce thee to yſſue forth of thy fortificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, &amp; to thy loſſe to bring out thy bands, &amp; to driue thee both to take thee to thy weapons
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:21658:38"/>and to faight. Surely it is a thing not litle to be regarded: but all diligence is to be vſed, that a ſigne, beinge geuen in the breake of daye, thy ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diours dee with meate comforte their ſtrengthe, leſte that being peraduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture aſſaulted, they be not conſtrained to arme them ſelues and to faight fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting. For the ſouldiours vndoubtedly being refreſſhed with a litle meate, &amp; not thereby full ſatiſfied and filde, be come in fayghte, bothe more luſtier, &amp; muche ſtronger. Of the whiche thing, making no coumpt, hath happened of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten times, that vnfortuna<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ly menne through famin, and lacke of meate be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing cleane without ſtrength, haue ben ouercome: and ſpeciallye when they come to the battaile that is no lyghte ſkirmiſhe, but that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinueth a whole daye.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>¶ Of comforting the Armie.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F at a time ſome malincoly bappe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to grow as is wonte to chaunce through ſome feare that appeareth to haue occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pied
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:21658:38"/>the mindes of fouldiours, or els through ſome ſocours come to the ene<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mies, or through ſome other cauſe where by the power of the aduerſaries might be thought ſuperiour to theirs, then ſpecially to a Captaine it is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſet, to ſhewe him ſelfe cherefull, &amp; pleaſant. Conſidering that the counti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nance &amp; loke of the Captaine, is wont to make the mindes of the ſouldiours conformable, for that altogether with his ſemblaunce, they are moued. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he being cherefull, ſodainly the ſouldiours take a good harte, iudging that nothing contrary nor porilous, maye fortune. So contrariwiſe, if it ſeeme that he be afraide or ſad, all by and by lacke harte, no otherwiſe, then if there appeared ſome great cuyne at hande. Wherfore ſurely it is better, &amp; doth more agree with the wiſdom of a Captaine, with the ſemblaunce of the face, to fayne cherefulneſſe vnto men, and with his merines, to make them glad, then with wordes and orations to comforte them, whyleſt they be af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted with malincoly. For as muche as vnto wordes, often tymes they doe not geue credite.</p>
            <pb n="68" facs="tcp:21658:39"/>
            <p>whiche accordinge as the condicion of the time requireth, maye moſte ſtudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly be fayned: but euery man ſpecial<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly beholdeth the countenance, and the boldnes that appeareth in the face, &amp; eſteaming that there is no faynednes, al feare ſet aſide, they aſſure them ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues in their minde. And out of doubt in a Captaine, it is to be deſired to haue the one and the other, that is to know, when nede is, to vſe to good purpoſe the facultye of ſpeache, and to ſhewe himſelfe ſuch a manne, as the tyme, and occaſion ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guire.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>VVhen it is meete to put the armie in feare and terrour.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Ike as it auay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth much with wordes and with chereful looke to gyue courage, and to fill with hope, the army
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:21658:39"/>in which is entred ſome fearfulnes, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo it is not of ſmal vtility, at a time to put them in feare, when they be ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to idelnes and ſlouthfulnes, litle eſteaminge the Generall Captaine, and the other Captaines, rendryng not obedience. Therfore then, with remembringe of perilles, and making alſo mention of the diligence of the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, it is fit to kepe them in feare, wherby thou ſhalt make thy ſouldiers not fearefull, but warefull. And like as the ſicke minde afflicted with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lincolie, is to be releued and holpen, with putting the ſame in good hope, euen ſo laſiuious menne, throughe ſlouth vnrulye, ought with terror to be refained and chaſtiſed. By which meane oftentimes chaunceth, that the Cowardes and Daſtardes, ſettyng a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide feare, become valiant, &amp; contrary wyſe, the bolde and couragious, is made prudent and politike. And bothe the one and the other, of theſe two thinges may happen, eyther that thy ſouldiers, after ſuch ſort doe feare y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> enemies that they haue no ſtomack to take in hand to do any thing, or els to deſpiſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo, &amp; paſſe ſo litle of them that they thynke not that they ſhould
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:21658:40"/>take anye heede. And therfore to eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye one of theſe two thynges, thou oughteſt circumſpectlye to frame thy ſelfe, and to haue regarde to the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires, and to the times, ſo that when nede ſhall require, bothe with wordes and with looke, to ſhew thy ſelfe to haue feare, and to forſee that whiche is to come: or els to ſeme bolde and hardye, when thou ſhalte know the ſame to be lyke to helpe thee.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>Howe Souldiers maye be incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged vvith priſoners of the enemies.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Litle before that they come to the poincte to faighte, ineſpeciallye when the vncertaine end of the day of battail that is to be made, cauſeth the
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:21658:40"/>Souldiers to be doubtfull and full of thoughtes, all diligence and policy is to be vſed, eyther with ſuddein aſſaul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, or with ambuſhes, or elles with ſome light ſkirmiſhe, to take ſome of the ennemies, of theym chiefelie, that haue lefte their places, appointed to the warde, which vſe ſomwhat abrode in the fieldes to ſtraggle, who, if thou ſhalt perceaue to be luſty &amp; bold, cauſe them to be put to death by and by, or els geue them bounde in cuſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to thoſe that haue the charge of pri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſoners, that they be diligently kept, &amp; commaund that no man be ſuffered to go to ſpeake with them. But if thou know that they be afraid, and altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vyle, geue commaundement then that quickly they may be brought vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thy lodging, and looking on theim ſcornefully, and with ſeuere and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled countenance, and alſo with thret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninges, after ſuch ſorte to bring them more in feare, and to make theym humbly to beſech thee with wepyng, and for doubt of their liues to be good vnto them, thou ſhalt cauſe them to be brought in the fight of thy Army, and
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:21658:41"/>ſhalt ſpeak vnto thy Souldiers, ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng them howe ſimple, vyle, fearfull, and of no worthynes the enemies be with whom they haue to faight, as theſe whiche feare ſo muche the ſtroke of death, and ſo muche diſtruſt them ſelues, that fallynge downe on their knees, with ſo muche vylenes, and ſo ſhamefully do pray to avoide the peril thereof, and to aſke mercy of their ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaries. Therfore a moſt likly thing it is, that therby, the Souldiers will take hart, and of the vituperus ſpecta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cle of ſuch made priſoners, will iudge of the vilenes, and delicatenes of the enemies. And ſurely, if a manne who hath not as yet ſene, doeth notwyth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding hope, how much more ought he to be moued by the thinge in dede, and with the recompence of hope, whereby light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye is taken awaye feare and diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultye.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="73" facs="tcp:21658:41"/>
            <head>How men ought to be ſet in araye.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eing many and ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dry waies of ordering me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in battel ray, which chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſeth through varie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of weapons, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the maner as the Souldiours are taught and accuſtomed, and according to the ſituation of the place, and the qualitye of the enemies: it is nedefull that the Captaine haue ſuch knowe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, that he maye vſe euerye one of them, when occaſion ſhall require.</p>
            <p>But I will brieflye declare thoſe thinges, that maye be conuenient to the diuers ſortes of weapons, at the pitchynge of the fielde, beſides thoſe thynges that maye be founde in the ſame neceſſitye of time.</p>
            <p>Ordaine then thy horſemen, not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to thy deſire, but as the time and the condicion of things ſhal con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain thee. Thou ſhalt put in aray thy horſemen againſt thoſe of thy enemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es: but as muche as maye be poſſible, ſet them in facion as they are wonte
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:21658:42"/>to ordeine y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> battailes with .ii. hornes, ſo that both on the fronte, and on the ſides, by the commodity of the large<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of the place, they maye more ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dely ride and manege their horſes, and not to put other behinde theym, that maye let them. In the mayne battaile place among the firſte, the Velitie, the whorlers of darts, and the croſbowes: finally the ſhooters in longe bowes, and the ſlingers. For that if ſuch kind of menne ſhoulde be placed hynder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt, they ſhould hurt more their fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes, then any of thenemies. And yf they be placed in the middeſt, their maner of faighting ſhoulde bee to no pourpoſe, for that they can not retire backewarde for the lengthe of theyr dartes and of their ſhotte, nor yet can not with their bodies moue them ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues to whorle, beyng let of them that go before. And muche leſſe the ſlin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers can wild their ſlinges or throw: being hindered of the Souldiers that ſtande aboute them, in the which, the ſwinge of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſling hurting men, ſhalbe of more damage to their felowes then to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> aduerſaries. Likwiſe the ſhooters if they ſhall be before the other, they wil hit almoſt in one marke, directly
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:21658:42"/>in the bodies of the ennemies, but if they ſtande in the laſt ranke, or in the midſt, they ſhalbe conſtrained to ſhoot aloft: in the which maner, the arowes flying compaſſe, their violence muſte nedes conſume in vaine: and while they fall downe, vppon the heades of the enemyes, the blowe hauing nowe loſt hys force, can ſcarſe do any maner of harme.</p>
            <p>If it happen that thou muſt fayght, in places where one partte is plaine and lowe, and the other by meane of lytle hylles, hygher then the playne, then ſpeciallye place thy Souldiers, that are lyghte armed, on the moſt rough and hyllye grounde. But yf thou be in the playne, and the enemye on the hilles, conduct the lyght armed Souldiers, as they whiche moſt eaſely canne throwe their dartes, and retire theim ſelues, and in runnyng apaſe &amp; ſpedilye go vppe in the roughe and ſtepe places, leauing in anye wyſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twene the bandes ſome diſtaunce: ſo that if peraduenture the ennemyes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byding to incounter thee, and to come to the faight, when thy Souldyers haue nowe throwen their dartes, and conſumed al their other kynde of ſhot,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:21658:43"/>tourninge backe thoſe bandes wyth order, and withoute diſturbaunce, cauſe that they may retire theym ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues for ſuccour in the hindermoſt par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of the Army. For vndoubtedlye, to go aboute with the Armye, and to turne it vpon a corner, is a thing that by no maner of meanes is ſure. For as muche as the enemies, may go before them, and before they be ioyned wyth the other part of the armye, by force maye breake them. Contrariwiſe, the paſſing ſtraightlye betwene the ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des cloſed together, being thicke, and as it were to fall vpon the weapons, may cauſe confuſion, and put in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order the rankes. But if the Velity aſſaulte the ennemyes by a wyng, they maye then doe exceading great harme, as thoſe that maye ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twhart whorle, and throw their dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, and conſequentlye hurt the naked partes of the enemies. Finally, the ſunges be more perniſius, then al the weapons that the Velity are wont to occupye. For that the colour of lead is like the colour of the aire, whereby whileſt ſuche bullettes of leade flie in the ayre, it is not ſene before it woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:21658:43"/>the enemy at a ſudden: &amp; through the force of the whirle, and ſwinge, &amp; violent mouinge thereof, as it were burninge, and fired, doth wound gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouſlye, and penitrateth inwardlye, nor it cannot be deſerued: for the lips of the wounde ſodeinly cloſeth, as one which making a ſigne with his eyes, ſhutteth them not fully.</p>
            <p>But if thou lacke ſuche ſort of wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon, and the aides of Velitie, and that the enemy be aboundantlye furniſhed of them, commaund that the foremoſt of thy battaile, goe forwarde thicke and cloſe together, bearing great ſhiel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des, with whiche, they maye couer all their bodyes, and the other that folow after them in araye, euen to the laſte, holding vp their targettes, ouer their heades, muſte paſſe ſo muche forward after this ſort, tyll they come within the whorle of the dartes. For as much as, beinge couered after thys maner, they can not be hurte in anye part by the ſhotte. But if the one and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther army haue plenty of Velitie: then cauſe thyne to be the firſte, to hurt the enemy, before they come nere to the handes, or els after the battaile is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon, geuinge the aſſaulte ouertwhart
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:21658:44"/>to do then what they can to hurte the enemyes, the which ſhalbe inforced to preſe together, and to bring them ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues into a litle ſpace, and moleſted of the weapons whorlde from farre of, ſhalbe conſtrayned to diſorder theym ſelues.</p>
            <p>If thou wylt auoyde that the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myes compaſſe thee not aboute, make not thy rankes longe, after ſuche ſorte, that altogether they become weake, that the ennemye maye caſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly breake theym, and thereby attayne the paſſage, and that he nede not foor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to ſeeke longer waye to gette to compaſſe thee, for as muche as, waye beyng geuen, and the order of thyne broken, he maye gene the charge vppon thy mennes backes, the which not only thou haſt to take bede of, that it chaunce thee not, but thou oughteſt to vſe meanes to do the lyke agaynſt the enemy.</p>
            <p>If ſometyme thou ſeeſt the order of thy men to be weake, do not retire nor drawe them together, after ſuch ſort, that the enemy maye compaſſe them, and ſhutte theym vppe rounde about,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:21658:44"/>onely it is nedefull for thee, to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne ſtrong the hyndermoſte par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, no leſſe, then thoſe, that fyrſte he placed in the heade, or in the ſydes. For as muche as the laſt and the reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuyng Souldiers, may ſtoppe the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myes ſuche waye, lyke as alſo maye they, whyche ſtande in the winges, and in the hornes, ſo that thou be at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiue to forſee for thynges to come, and inlargyng the hindermoſte parte of the battayle, and deſtending bothe the flankes, ſette thy Souldyers tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned agaynſt the battaile of the enne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myes, and commaunde thoſe that nowe of the ennemyes bee compaſſed aboute, that they tourne theyr bac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes, to the backes of them whyche go before them, and ſo to faight on euery ſyde.</p>
            <p>It appertayneth to a circumſpecte and prudent Captayne, when he ſhall know to haue to fayght wyth a fewe menne agaynſte a greate multytude, to vſe eyther dylygence to chuſe ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che fytte places, whyche bee ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther neare Rockes of Ryuers, or elles vnder Mountaynes, and vppon
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:21658:45"/>all other thinges, where thou mayſte put in aray thy battailes, and by the qualitie of the place, be able to let the ennemies, that they neither compaſſe thee about, nor incloſe thee. For as muche as a fewe, the whiche haue to occupy the highe and craggy places, maye eaſelye withſtande the power of the enemies, that ſhoulde with multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude attempt to compaſſe thee. In the whiche thing, it is not only nedefull the councel and prudence of the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, but it requireth a greate deale more good fortune. Becauſe that often times peraduenture chaunceth, that an Army happeneth vpon ſuche fitte places, and notwithſtanding the cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine is ignoraunt how to chuſe what ſituacion of grounde is beſt for him. But of thoſe that are preſent to chuſe the beſt, and to foreſee whiche to him is lykeſt to be moſt profitable, is ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a ſigne of a wiſe Captaine.</p>
            <p>Some of a cuſtome when they go to faighte, truſting to the great number of men: haue ſet them in araye after the maner of a half circull, ſuppoſyng to be able to intiſe the enemies after ſuch ſort, as though they ſhould come to fayght man for manne, in the whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:21658:45"/>maner mouing them ſelues, they thinke by a litle and a litle bending the corners of the halfe circle of their battel, ioyning them together in a cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, to incloſe in the ſame their aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries. Againſt whome, it is not mete to goe with like facion of battaile: but deuiding thy men in thre partes, with the two, the charge may be geuen vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the one and the other wing of the ennemies: the thirde thou ſhalte ſet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the halfe circle, whiche ſtande ſtil, and go not forward, and if the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies wil ſtand ſtil in the facion of a ſemicircle: thoſe ineſpecially that are in the midſt, ſhall do no harme: where in dede is taken from them all way to be able to doe any thing. But if they begin to moue, whileſt they would fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the bottome of the halfe circle, reduce them ſelues by right line, preſſing the one the other, they ſhall breake theyr aray. For as much as, ſtanding ſtill, the order of them, that be placed by the flankes bowed like a horne, and they faighting, the halfe circle by no manner of waye maye be reduced in righte order. The araye then broken, and mouing theym ſelues, from the halfe Circle confuſedlye, thou ough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:21658:46"/>with that thyrde part, to aſſaulte them ſo diſordered. But if the enemies ſtand ſtill in the ſemicircle, ſet againſt them, lyght armed Souldiours, and alſo whorlers of Dartes, whiche may opreſſe them with multitude of darts, and with other weapons that may be ſhotte or whorled from farre of. All be it, if with all theſe force of bothe thy bandes thou aſſaulte the enemies on the ſyde, and ſo go againſte this order of halfe circle, thou doeſt not erre ther in one whitt. For as much as they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not able to come to fayght againſt thee with all their men, wyll deuyde them ſelues, and only they that were ſette on the ſydes, ſhalbe conſtrayned to be the firſt to come to the faighte, for conſideration of the aſſault, which thy men haue gyue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them on the ſides. But peraduenture it wyll not bee a thynge of litle vtilitie, that ſome time putting firſt men in araye, no other wyſe then if thou wouldeſt fayghte, and after as it were for feare retiring backe and keping the raye, thou fayne a retire like to a running awaye, and then turning thee to come to affronte thoſe which folowe thee. For as much
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:21658:46"/>as ſome tyme, the enemies thinkinge that the armie of the aduerſaries for feare be put in flight, through vnme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurable gladnes, breaking their order will geue the onſet, &amp; euery man will ſtriue and inforce him ſelfe to get be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his felow. Againſt whome by that meanes, thou mayeſt faight without peril, and through the boldenes of thy ſtaying, contrary to the opinion of the enemies, thou maieſt eaſely diſconfite them, now being become fearefull, &amp; ſchattered here &amp; there, although they had before ſo proudly perſued thee.</p>
            <p>Beſides all this, there would be in a readines certaine Souldiours elec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, which ſtanding in aray out of the battell as Triarii, ſhould geue ſuccor to that parte of thine, whiche are we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye and repulſed, and of whome when nede requires, thou maieſt eaſely haue helpe. Conſidering that it is the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt ayde that may be, to ioyne vnto wery men, thoſe whiche are luſtie, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that they commodiouſly may ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour their fellowes nowe wery: and freſhe and vigorouſly aſſault ſtrongly the enemies deſpearſed and becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men weake.</p>
            <pb n="84" facs="tcp:21658:47"/>
            <p>And it is not only to good purpoſe, but rather a thing of great benefite, if ſome men of thyne be apoincted to lay them ſelues ſecretlye in ambuſſhe in ſome place ſo farre of, as maye bes thought mete: to whome commaunde, whyleſt with thy battaill ſet in array, thou ſhalt bee comen to hande ſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes, ſo ſoone as the ſigne is geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that they diſcouering them ſelues, do quick<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly come vnto thee. Whiche then is to be done: when ſuccor looked for, ſemes not to come at a due tyme. For that the aduerſaries, ſuppoſing thoſe, to be the ſame men, that thou lokedſt ſhuld haue comen in thy ſuccour, perauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture whyleſt they as yet march, before they be ready to ioyne with the reſt of thy Armie, wyl be afraide &amp; put them ſelues in flight, thinking them to bee no ſuche nomber, as in dede they be, but a great deale bigger, and ſpecially if it be done at a ſudden, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they are about y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> feates of Armes. For as much as ſuche chaunce, is wonte to make a frayde the myndes of them, whiche haue not experience of thinges, doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting leſte there happen them not ſome worſe thing, and therefore with feare they abide the ende of the matter.</p>
            <pb n="85" facs="tcp:21658:47"/>
            <p>The aſſaulting the enemies behind at vnawares, bringes them in excea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge great terrour, and aboue all thinges is of vncredible profit. For which thing, if it were poſſible to do, there ſhould be ſent by nyght a bande of Souldiers, that trauerſing y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> waye, might paſſe beyonde the enemies, and behind them, place them ſelues in ambuſſhe: And when bothe the armies were affroonted, and nowe comen to the faighte, they quickelye marching out of the wayte, ſhoulde aſſalte the hyndermoſte bande of the enemies: whom compaſſed about on euery ſide, although that there were lefte them ſome hope to ſaue them ſelues: they ſhall not haue ſtomacke to goe about to flye, but to yelde, as they who are not able to retire backe, nor commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly goe forwarde, beynge of euerye ſyde ouertaken.</p>
            <p>Whyleſt the faighte continuallye doth increaſe, and that of neither part they beare not theym ſelues vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>auntly, thou rydinge rounde aboute, ſhalt comtorte thy men, and being on the ryght wynge: ſhalt crye, that the lefte is victorious, and that the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies nowe are ouercome. If thou be
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:21658:48"/>on the lefte wyng, declare that the bande of the ryght wyng of thy men hath obtained the victory, not paſſing whether it be true or falſe. For that it is not much amiſſe, nor of ſmall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moditie to vſe a ly, when the fayghte is greatly moued. Moreouer if the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitain or king of the enemies, be ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what farre from thee, or in the other wyng, or els in the middeſt of the bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taile, thou muſt crie with a loude voi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce (ſo that of the enemies thou be alſo hearde) that he is ſlaine. The whiche being openly vnderſtodde, thy menne more cherefully wil double their wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thines to faight, and the enemies will lacke hart, and altogether for deſpera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion will put them ſelues to flighte. This pollicie hath been often times profitable, where at one time, is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giled the enemies &amp; thine own men, to theſe ſhewing things of ſauegarde, and to the other hurtefull and dolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous.</p>
            <p>Lykewyſe, it is the office of a wyſe Capitaine, in the arayes, to place to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether the brothers with brothers, &amp; frendes with frendes. For that why<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt we ſee that he is brought in peril, to whome we beare good will, of loue
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:21658:48"/>inforced, fearing no manner of daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, more valiauntly we put forward our ſelues to defende him. And he ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him ſelfe ſo louinglye defenved, will be aſhamed, and doubte, that yel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding not the like kyndnes, may ſeeme to be negligente wyllingly, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he wyll thinke it a great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proche vnto him, to forſake his frende that ſo redely hathe done for him, &amp; ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully to geue hym ſelfe to flye.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>Of commaundementes, wauinges, and Signes.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He commaunde<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ments, wauinges, and ſignes, ought likewyſe firſt to be geuen to the heads &amp; leaders of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, for as much as to go to finde euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maund them lyke things, ſhuld be a manifeſt token of a Captain very ſimple &amp; vnexpert: ſeing that whyleſt to enery one ſeperatly y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts at geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, time co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſumeth &amp; great rumor therby is made, al aſking him at ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d,
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:21658:49"/>and ſekinge euery one to know what the commaundementes are. There happeneth beſides this, that certaine menne to the commaundementes, wil adde ſome thing, or els through igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce, diminiſhe them. Wherfore it is meete that the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundements, be geuen firſt to the heades and rulers, &amp; after they to refer them to thoſe that are vnder them, and thoſe likewiſe to doe the ſame from hand to hand, to al the other. And in this manner, the ſignes and commaundementes maye go from one to another euen to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> laſt. For that not ſo ſoone as they are ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, but alſo without noyſe, and with order euery one ſhall come to knowe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge therof. The which likewiſe in geuing tokens with fire, is wonte to be obſerued, where the firſt litle fire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brande is lifted vp, the ſecond hauing receaued the brande, geueth it to the thirde: the thirde to the fourth, which geueth it to the fifte, the fyfte to the ſixt, &amp; ſo forth, the one after the other, after ſuch ſort, that in ſhort time from a moſt great diſtaunce, the ſigne had of the firſt, ſhall come euen to the laſt ordinarilye and without diſturbance. Likwiſe that ſigne which ought to be
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:21658:49"/>geuen the third, after the commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, ſhould not be geuen with any thing doone by the voyce, but either with ieſture of bodye, or by ſigne of the head, or with mouing of the hande, or with ſtriking together the armes, or with turning of the Spear, or els with glittering of the ſwerde: ſo that peraduenture making tumulte not onelye the Souldiours oughte to ſtande attentiue to take the wauing, but alſo the ſigne. For as much as the enemies might vnderſtande the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the wauing, whiche they may oftentimes ſee to be geuen. But the ſigne whiche beſides may ſecretly bee geuen, after ſuche ſorte that it cannot be knowen of the enemies, ſemes alſo to be very conuenient and c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mmodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, for the ſtraunge Souldiours to knowe: whome although they vſe diuerſe languages, notwithſtanding they being confederates and ſeruing together with you: and being not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to ſpeake as they maye bee vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtode, nor vnderſtande other, which in other language ſpeake, by making ſig<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes, the fredes by frendes, may by ſuch meane deſerne their meaning. The which ſignes oughte to be geuen and
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:21658:50"/>diſtributed not at ſuch time whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they muſt faight, and make noyſe with vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain voyces amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the handes, that are to be ſet in araye, but long before when quietly they remayn at leyſure.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>Of the order that is to be obſerued.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eſides all this commaunde thy Souldi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ours to go forward, and turne backwarde with good order: wherby be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing repulſed, and retyring, they maye be leſſe hurte, as thoſe whom the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my one by one, can not oppreſſe, being not here and there ſcattred, and diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derlye wandering: or if they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing conquerers, ſhall purſue the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myes out of order, and put to flyghte, they ſhall ouerthrowe them eaſely, &amp; more ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gly oppreſſe them, and with more ſafegarde, if in the chaſe vnited together, and in araye they proceade. For vndoubtedly many times, when the enemy fliyng, ſeeth his aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, come vpon him without anye or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, he bryngyng agayne his menne in araye, &amp; turning backwarde with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding them with viole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, crusly o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uercometh them. Wherfore men muſt
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:21658:50"/>thinke that nothing is better, nothing more ſafer, nothing more ſurer, then obſeruing the order, to ſtande ſtill in their place appointed: &amp; to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary nothing is more perillous, nor more hurtfull, then to breake the order, &amp; to forſake the ſame place.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>Of making ready and ſetting foorth the armie to faight the fielde.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>aue care to bring thy Armie to the fielde with bright and ſhining armor. which eaſly may be done by co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forting thy ſoldiours to make clean their ſwerds, headpeſes, corcelettes, &amp; euerye other peeſe of Armor, for as muche as the cleanes and brightnes therof, maketh the Armie ſeeme terrible, and putteth feare &amp; trauaile in the myndes of the enemies. Moreouer cauſe thy handes to go forwarde with rumors, &amp; ſhow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinges, and ſometime running with violence, for as muche as the ſembla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of ſuch thinges, the cryinges &amp; noyſeof barnes, and the ſoundes of trompets, wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>derfully troubleth and feareth the hartes of the aduerſaries.</p>
            <pb n="92" facs="tcp:21658:51"/>
            <p>When thou ſhalt come to the point to ioyne battell with the enemy, cauſe thy ſouldiers ſomewhat before, to flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhe ofte their naked ſwerdes againſt the ſunne. For y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the gliſtering ſwerds and their ſhining poinctes, through the brightnes, now of the one, &amp; nowe of the other, againſt the reſplending beames of the ſunne, doth ſhew a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine horrible terror of warre. The which thing, if as well of the enemye ſhall likewiſe be doone, aunſwering thee with the verye ſame, thou haſte cauſe to be afrayd: &amp; if he doe not that, it is to be thought that thou in anye wyſe muſt nedes thereby put him in drede. Being ſet in aray, &amp; as well of the one as of the other parte, the men being made redy to faight, thou ough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt not ſodenly to moue thee, being drawen w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> deſire to be the firſt to geue the onſet, but ſtay thee nere thy tre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ch, till that thou ſeeſt thy ſelf the redines of the enemies, that is how manye, of what co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dition, &amp; finally in what place they be diſpoſed to faight, ſeing that after this maner, thou mayſt more co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modiouſly forſee to thy affaires, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering which of thine thou haſt to ſet againſt thoſe of the enemy, &amp; in what
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:21658:51"/>maner thy men is to be placed &amp; ordei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, doing in like ſort as is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenient for a good Phiſition to do, the which conſidering firſt, &amp; knowing the infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, cometh after to giue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> remedies. Ordeine thy menne accordyndyng as thou perceiueſt to turne moſt vtilitie to thy buſines. For as much as the cap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>taine oftentimes hauing ſeen the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration of thenemies, is conſtrayned to accomodate, &amp; to ordein his ſoldiers according to the Army, the men, &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. If the enemy be more pui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaunt of horſemen, &amp; that thou perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tur haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>moditie, chuſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſtraight and difficulte places, or at the foote of mountaines, &amp; where the horſes ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not eaſely go: but if thou haue not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie ſo to do, proceade ſo much forward faighting, till thou finde places mete and conuenient for thy neceſſitie. But within the trenche, leaue the warde, for defence of the lodgings &amp; of the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages, leſt that the enemy vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ding the place to be forſake<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſende his ſouldiers to take thy campe, left with out defence, &amp; to ſpoile al thy cariages.</p>
            <p>Some captaines deſtroy their owne lodginges, or elles paſſe Riuers, or deliberately do leue behinde the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hilles and depe places, to the ende that the
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:21658:52"/>Souldiours ſtanding conſtantly, may ouercom the aduerſaries, &amp; attaine the victorie, or otherwiſe altogether to pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhe. For that if they thinke to ſaue them ſelues by running awaye, they ſhall ſee that by al maner of wayes to be taken from them, the poſſibilitie to ſcape. Theſe maner of men ſurely I of the one part can not prayſe much, nor yet of the other parte diſprayſe: for as muche as deliberately to purpoſe to do thinges with peryll, is rather re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted fooliſh hardines then prudence, and vnto fortune, there is more to bee attributed then to good iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. For as muche as where thou arte co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to do the one of theſe two thinges either with all thy power faighting, to attain the victory, or els being ouer come, euery thing to goe to ruyn, in what maner may I the victory vnto prudence, or els the ruine &amp; vniuerſall conflict vnto the election and to iudge me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t aſcribe? Yet ſurely, I ſuppoſe that ſometime to ſome ſouldiers, it ought to be permitted that for deſire of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor &amp; glory, periluſly they may faight: when the care is ſuch, that if they bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues valiantly, ſhal get vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon weale no ſmal vtilitie, &amp;
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:21658:52"/>if they vnfortunatly faight, that it can not turne to much hurt. But fortune being doubtful &amp; vncertain, &amp; doubtful the ſucces of the battel, I praiſe not in any maner of wyſe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> haſarding with all thy men, in the handes of chaunce. And me thinkes they erre exceadingly which will faight after ſuch ſort, that if they ſhal haue ouercome, it ſeemeth them to haue litle hurt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> enemies: but if they ſhalbe ouerthrowen &amp; vanqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, to be like to be of moſt great hurt to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon weale: and yet they leue not to vſe like policies of warre. But if now it be ſeen plainly, and may be taken for a moſte certaine thing, that great diſcomfiture is like to folow, if y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> doe not faight, although it be with per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rill, &amp; that if the enemy ſhal once be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uercom, he is like altogether to periſh, then me thinkes, that thoſe captaines do not amiſſe, which againſt their ſoul diers ſhould ſtoppe the waye for being able to flie. For that in a thing vncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, it is better with ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>lenes, not on<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly to auoyde the miſchief, but rather to ſeke to offend y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> enemy, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ſtand in idelnes, &amp; to behaue thy ſelfe vyle, when thou mayſt be ſure, that daring to do nothing, thy buſines are like al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together to go to naught.</p>
            <pb n="96" facs="tcp:21658:53"/>
            <p>But not only in like places, where flying hath no certainty of ſafegarde, but in euery place, and in condicions of faightynge, thou oughteſt to admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhe thy Souldiers, and with all rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to ſhewe theym, that to thoſe that flie, doeth followe nothing but death manifeſt and certaine: becauſe the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies haue libertye to perceuer and purſue them, &amp; being not letted of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye, maye eaſely offende their aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries, ſcattered and put in flight, and that to them who faighting, ſtand ſtil and do defend, there death is doubtful and the perill vncertaine. And if thou perſwadeſt them, that in the battaile which is to be fought, thoſe that geue them ſelues to flye, wythout faile ſhal moſt ſhamefullye periſhe, and he that ſtandeth ſtedfaſte, in the ende if the worſt fall, ſhall die moſt gloriouſlye: and that to them whiche forſake their place, and not to thoſe whiche keepe araye, ſhall inſue the hurte, thou ſhalt perceiue to haue them in the ſelf ſame perils, both bolde and valiant. Therefore deſire to haue thy Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers perſwaded and diſpoſed after this maner. For as muche as thoſe that be of thys minde, and of ſuche affection,
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:21658:53"/>eyther they attaine the vyctorye ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye, or els ſuffer litle harme.</p>
            <p>Surely the Councels founde in the inſtaunt perill while they are a faigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting &amp; the for caſts for to put at a ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den againſt the deuiſe of the enemies, haue without doubt to the Captaines and to them that well vnderſtand the feates of warre, brought foorth more excellent glory, &amp; greater maruel, then thoſe haue d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n that a man wold haue thought, &amp; by coniecture ſuppoſed to haue bene exceading good before that men come to the trial, whiche thing, to ſhew one by one, and to euery man to geue ſeuerall inſtructions, is verye difficult. For like as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maſters of ſhips hauing prepared &amp; diſpoſed by order al things that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of nauigation re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires, after departing out of the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, do put themſelues to the mayne ſea: but if peraduenture there happen to riſe ſome tempeſt: they doe not that they deſire, but the ſame whiche they are driuen to doe, and they doe manye thinges boldly, and beynge rounde a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boute ouercome with perylles, wyth ſtoute mynde, they reſiſte with theyr prouiſions, vſyng not ſo muche the memorye and the ſcience of ſailying,
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:21658:54"/>as the occaſion, whiche vnlooked for, appeareth before theym: Euen ſo the Captains muſt doe: Put in order his men, and indeuor theym, and diſpoſe them in that manner, which he thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth to tourne commodious and profi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>table to him, and to his affaires: but when the tempeſte ouertaketh him, and the waightenes of the battayle, for as much as, many thinges by force is wont to chaunge and breake, and greate varietie to fall, then according to the ſtate of thinges preſent, and that is ſeene before the eyes, he muſte fynde at a ſudden, according to oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion, the forecaſt and councels, more rather as neceſſitie of fortune, then as the arte and witte it ſelfe, ſhall haue offred him.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>Of the Captaynes office, vvhileſt the battayle is a faightyng.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>Nto the captain it is mete rather circom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectly &amp; with wiſdome, then boldly to faight, or to refrayne altogether from the faight: Becauſe that faigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:21658:54"/>cannot ſo much benefite the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon weale, although he ſhoulde ſhew force inuincible, as loſing his lyfe not a litle ſhould indamage the ſame.</p>
            <p>Wherefore, he ought to be much va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lianter with prudence of mynde, then with the force and luſtines of bodye. For as muche as, with the worthines and ſtrength of bodye, the Souldiers may doe ſome greate attempt, but the vſing of prudence and to foreſee thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and deliberating in tymes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient to councel the common weal, principally to the Captaine, and to no other is requiſite. For that lyke as if the Mayſter of a ſhyppe leauyng the ſterne, &amp; forſaking the gouerning, wil do thoſe things that appertaine to the other mariners, ſhall without doubt geue occaſion to drown the ſhyp, euen ſo the very ſame errour the Captayne ſhoulde commit, who ſetting a parte his offyce of Councellyng, for prouy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding euery thing, ſhuld defend ſo low to take y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> charge which is mete for ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers. And ſurely the preſumtious nec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> greater &amp; ſuperiors in dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, maketh to become vaine all aid, wherin neceſſarily is commytted the conſeruacyon of wayghtye affaires.
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:21658:55"/>The like I repute ought to be though of that Captaine without anye diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, the which when he ſhalbe dead, the common weale to bee in haſard to fall in decaye, nor beyng not deade, no other then he ought to take thoughte for the ſafegard of the ſame. And ſuch a one by more reaſon is to be blamed as a ſimple captaine, then to be pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed as ſtoute. And ſurely he that hath done the duetye of a Captaine, wyth counſel, and with diſcretion, hauyng atchiued felicity, by mean of foreſight w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> reaſon he may lawfully glory. But contrariwyſe, he that is ſo arrogant &amp; couetous, that beleueth not to be able to doe anye thing honorable, if he him ſelfe go not to faighte with the enne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mye, not onelye is not to be thought valiant, but rather preſumpteous and foolyſhe hardie. And that he ſo dothe to get him ſelfe a name of the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, not to eſteme any peril, for to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage his Souldiers, both to make them redy &amp; glad, to ieopard them ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues in an enterpriſe. But let him that wil do wel, faight warely, &amp; not feare death, &amp; chuſe ſooner to remain depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of his lyfe, then hauing any ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwe, to liue with ſhame. But the
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:21658:55"/>thing being ſafe, and the army in ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard, he ought to haue regard to his lyfe. For ſurely where the death of the Captayne chaunceth, there manye ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, the reputacion of the happy ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe is diminyſhed. For as muche as, they, who haue vnfortunatly fought, hauing vnderſtoode that the enemyes are lefte depriued of their Captayne, taking hearte agayne, haue aſſaulted them, &amp; theſe of the other part afflyc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with malincolye, haue lacked ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke, that althoughe they haue for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunately fought before, notwythſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding for the death of the Captain, they haue then put them ſelues in diſpaire.</p>
            <p>
               <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto the captain it likewiſe apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth whileſt his men faight, to go riding about the battel, to ſhew hym ſelfe to the faighters, to prayſe thoſe which valiauntly haue behaued them ſelues, to threaten the fearful, to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort thoſe that be doubtful &amp; ſlowe, to geue ſuccor to them that are repulſed, to ſupply the lackes, &amp; if it ſhalbe nede ful, to lead men from one place to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, to obſerue tymes, to take occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, to make coniecture of thinges to come, and to commaund when nede is that there be geuen the ſigne to retire</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="103" facs="tcp:21658:56"/>
            <head>Of that vvhich is to be done after the deede of Armes.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter that he hath reuoked the Souldyers from the faighte, let him do ſacrifice, &amp; geue order that thanks may be ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred to the immortall Gods, with ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne pompe, as muche as in that time maye be done, promyſing with gratefull minde, to make ſatiſfaction in thoſe thynges, ſo ſoone as the war is ended, and the victory obtained, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordyng to the conuenyent cuſtome of ſatiſfying. After warde let him geue honours and rewardes to them, why<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che he ſhall vnderſtande haue behaued them ſelues valiauntlye in the dede of Armes, and according to the cuſtome, to be towardes them benigne, and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berall. But thoſe whiche haue bene ſlacke and fearefull, let him punnyſhe moſt ſhamefully. Vnto valiaunt men let him graunt thoſe honours which according to the vſe of the countrie are
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:21658:56"/>lowed. The gyfies which the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain ought to geue, be theſe: armours, Anſignes, ſpoiles, the offices of Decu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians, Centuriaus, prouoſtes, conduc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters and other lyke offices. But to the moſt valiant, &amp; to thoſe that are alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy in authority, there would be grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter honors diſtrybuted, and to the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate Souldiers, to be geuen the leſſe. Although theſe thinges haue bene ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed to bee geuen liberallye, and with gentelnes, according to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruinges of euery man, neuertheleſſe it doth prouoke moreouer other vnto vertue, whiche of lyke honours are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous.</p>
            <p>And without doubt, when rewards are geuen to the good, for their meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, and the yll not ſcaping withoute puniſhment, of neceſſitye the armie is put in moſte excellent good hope. For that ſome for feare of pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, do abſtaine from doing yl, and other ſome drawen with the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of honoures, imbrace ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="104" facs="tcp:21658:57"/>
            <head>Of the Victorie.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Auing obtained ſome victorie, thou ough teſt not onely to euerye Souldiour particularly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o geue rewardes for the acte well executed, but alſo to all the Armie, thou oughteſt benignely to geue ſome generall rewarde for their labours. Thou ſhalt graunte licence to thy Souldiours, to putte to ſacke the lodginges of the enemies, the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages, and the Caſtels, if any by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of warre happen to come into thy poſſeſſion, and finally alſo the citie: ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uing that if peraduenture of the ſame there ſhould not be had more conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of deliberting ſome th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng. For that this to al ſuch affaires, is of much vtilitie, in eſpecially, when the warre is not as yet finiſhed. Becauſe the ſoul diours by ſuch profite and gaine allu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, will ſhe we them ſelues much ted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier &amp; more couragious in other occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions: if thou be not of opinion that it is proffitable for the hunters with the bloude and interiours of the wilde beaſtes whiche they haue kylled, to
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:21658:57"/>teach their hounds to hunt, but think it hurtful to geue in pray to the victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryous Souldiers the goods of theym whiche haue bene ouercome.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>Of putting thynges to ſacke.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Raunte not ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence to thy Souldiers neyther alwayes, nor in euery place, nor al to put to ſacke: &amp; permit not the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to come to lead alway the people: who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou maiſt cauſe to be ſolde (if nede re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire) for the common profite, and to maintain great expences. In whiche cace, thou ſhouldeſt commaund openly that al the goods be brought and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueyed vnto thee: Becauſe moſt excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentlye well, thou mayeſt deliberate thereof, hauing regarde to the time, &amp; to the ſtate of thinges, whether thou haſt nede to retayne all the praye, or part of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſame, or els none at al. And it is not conuenient, that making war the common treaſure be left wythout money, for Souldiers being depriued of the gaynes, which from day to day
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:21658:58"/>they make, eſpeciallye when by the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundant riches of them who are ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, &amp; by the fertelity of the places, the gaynes more amply, or largelye, and with more benignity may be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtributed to them.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>Of priſoners.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>O longe as the warre co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinueth, kyl not thy pryſoners, and ineſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially thoſe, againſte whome the war is made at the firſt, althoughe it happen that the confederates ſhall haue opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to cauſe them to be put to death. But aboue al things thou ough teſt not to put them to death, which a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> enemyes be of great aucthority &amp; of fame well knowen, &amp; notable, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membryng that fortune is vncertaine and doubtfull, and chaunce variable and mutable: the whiche moſte of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentymes loueth greatlye to beare enuy to the happye ſucceſſes, and to
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:21658:58"/>miniſter ſhame to glory attained. But ſeeke to exchaunge theym, or by ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring them, to get ſome Caſtel, or els to redeme thy frendes taken priſoners whom thou deſyreſt greatlye to haue againe, but if the ennemyes ſhall refuſe ſuch permutacion, then lykewiſe with reaſon thou mayeſt make reuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gement of their iniury.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>Of feastes, and triumphes, after the victorye.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Aungers being paſt and ouercome, and wyth greate trauayles hauing gotten the vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torye, lette thers be for thy Souldiers, made readye ſolemne feaſtes, and the places with good or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to be appointed, and geue ſuch or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that playes &amp; triumphes be made, ſo that hauing now the certaine ende
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:21658:59"/>of the victorie accompliſſhed, and the Souldiours knowyng thoſe thinges, whiche after the victory they haue to inioye, may for ſuche cauſe, learne to ſuſtain at another tyme, the difficultie of the turmoyles of warre.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>Of buriyng them whiche in the bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayle haue been ſlayne.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hou muſt after prouide, &amp; with great di<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ligence procure, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> obſequies be made moſt worſhypfullye to theim whiche haue been ſlayne in the deede of Armes, nor thou ſhouldeſt make ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe, neither of tyme nor of howre, nor of place, nor of perrill, whether thou ouercome, or be ouercomed. For that like as it is a godly thing, to performe the obſequies, &amp; according to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ryghts to doe ſacrifice for the dead, euen ſo it is very profitable for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that remaine aliue, and rather altogether neceſſary to ſhewe to the lyuing, this thy pitie to wardes the dead. For ſurely, when euery man ſeeth the dead bodies, as it
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:21658:59"/>w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>ere for outragiouſnes and deſpite of the Captaine, not to be buried, they iudge and preſuppoſe the very ſame of them ſelues, &amp; take diſpleaſure of ſuch thynges, knowyng that if they faigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting for their countrie, happen to be killed, are lyke not to be buried.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>Of reuenging the ouerthrowe.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>F in fayghting, thou happen to receiue ſome ouerthrowe, meſte dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly thou ſhouldeſt geue attendau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, to find occaſion to make reuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gement, and to take awaye the ſhame receiued, hauing nede after this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, to comforte thy Souldiers, which ſhalbe lefte thee ſafe. And ſurely moſte often times, thoſe that newly haue ob<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tayned the victory, are wont here and there to ſtraggell negligently, and to kepe their thyngs without forecaſt or any warde. And he that paſſeth lytle on y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> enemy, becometh with al, ſlouth full and recheles. For the which thing many tymes, the happy ſucceſſe of the
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:21658:60"/>Acte, hath been of greater harme then the receiued ruin. For that whoſoeuer hath once been beaten with contrarye fortune, by the ſucceſſe of the thing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing taught and admonyſhed of his er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, from that tyme forwarde, more warely doth gonerne him ſelfe. And contrariwyſe, he that hath not made proofe of aduerſity, ra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not vprightly in proſperous affaires maintein himſelf. And if he be a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>queror, as one that is become proud, he paſſeth litle of other nor vſeth not diſcreſſion after ſuche ſort, that no maner of hurte be taken, the which he ſhould haue vſch for to offende the vnwarefull and idell ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies. For ſurely to feare where is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>defull, and where the tyme requires, is token of a man, whiche wyſely pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uideth for his buſines. But without good conſideration, to deſpyſe &amp; make litle accompt of euery thyng, is the ſigne vndoubtely of an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogant man, and therfore ſuch a one, becommeth ſubiect to euery ſort of perill.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="111" facs="tcp:21658:60"/>
            <head>Of Truce.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>F thou haſt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de truce, doe not in anye wyſe all that tyme, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſault the enemy, nor yet ſtande vnprouided. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though towardes hym thou ſhouldeſt be in quiet, no otherwyſe then as yf thou haddeſt peace. But in as muche as appertayneth to thee, beware after ſuche maner as if thou madeſt warre, that there happen thee not any thing contrarie.</p>
            <p>And vndoubtedlye, it is a conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient thyng in tyme of Truce, that thou fyrſt moue not agaynſt the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mye, further then honeſtie and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonablenes, nor to ſtande altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther without order and diſarmed, but rather ſhewe thy ſelfe to take heade, and to haue ſuſpition of hydden ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred, and of the deceytes of the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaries.</p>
            <p>Foraſmuch as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mindes of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb n="112" facs="tcp:21658:61"/>thou haſte made truce, be ſecrete and vncertaine: for the whiche thing thou ſhouldeſt ſtedfaſtly obſerue, not to doe anye inturie, for the othe that thou haſte made in the couenauntes: but for feare of vntrueth, truſt not vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the enemies, wherein declare thy ſelfe withall, heedefull and prudent, not breaking the agreement, and lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinge not occaſion to be aſſaulted.</p>
            <p>Surely thoſe, whiche of the iniurye that peraduenture they are lyke to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue, do remytte the reuenge to the immortall Gods, although they be of a godlye oppinion, notwithſtanding me thinkes, they put not their things in ſafegard, where it is very ſtraunge and a foolyſhe thinge, not to defende thy ſelfe from perilles, &amp; to take no heede, becauſe thou haſte hope, that for their falſeheade, and breakynge of faith they are to be puniſhed, which vnmercifully haue offended and inda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maged thee, as thoughe it were lyke to turne thee to profite and ſafetye, ſo ſoone as the enemies ſhall haue ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red paine for the ſame, ſpecially when with ſafegarde of thy thynges, it is lawful for thee, to make proofe, and to come to knowledge of the impietye of the ennemyes. In whiche manner
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:21658:61"/>thou being falſelye and trayterouſlye aſſaulted, ſhalte not be hurte, and the enemy ſhal ſhew himſelfe to be diſleal, which hadde thought to haue hurt thee, if he hadde bene able.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>How the Captayne ſhoulde be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haue him ſelfe, to cauſe Cities to yelde.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>Syng benignity and gentelnes towardes thoſe Cities, whiche of their owne minde, haue yelded them-ſelues vnto thee, and by couenaunts being rendred-ſhall come into thy poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion, thou ſhalt therby incline other ſo to do. For y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> they intiſed of hope to attaine the verye ſame that the other haue, will eaſely yeld. And ſurely that manne, which ſo ſoone as he hath ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained a City, ſheweth himſelfe ſharp and cruell, putting it to ſacke, tearing and cuttyng to peces al thinges, ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth occaſion to other Cities, to alie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:21658:62"/>their good willes, and to take v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon them ſelues the warre, and the difficulte victorye. For as muche as, euery man which is aſſured, that the conquerour is vnmercifull and cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell towardes them whome he hath o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uercome, doth chuſe muche rather to doe and to ſuffer all extremitye, then willinglye to yelde. And queſtionles, no one thyng filleth ſo much the mind with valiauntneſſe, as feare of the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent perill, whiche euery man kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth to ſuffer when ſo euer they yeld. And the feare to ſuffer miſery, is wont to put in the mindes of men great de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire bothe to make reſiſtaunce and to faight. And all proofe whiche is made againſt deſperates, is difficult and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rillous. And they who yelding theym ſelues cannot hope to be intrered more gentlye, nor to haue vſed towardes them more benignity then as if faigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, they were ouercome, much ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther making reſiſtence, wil ſuffer all miſchiefe. Whereby the vnwiſe and cruell Captaynes, geueth occaſyon that the ſiege of a Citie is prolonged, and ſome alſo to become vayne, and are neuer brought to good end, and be likewiſe daungerous and perillous.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="115" facs="tcp:21658:62"/>
            <head>Of keping promiſe with Traitours</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>Nto them which at thy requeſt, ſhall haue committed ſome treaſon, thou oughteſt to obſerue the faithe and promiſes made theym, not ſo muche for their cauſe, as for the time to come, wherby other maye vnderſtande, that thoſe whiche wil folowe thy part, ſhalbe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded, and ſo the eaſelier they will be brought to ſuche ſeruices. For que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtionleſſe he that geueth to tratours, may thereby receyue great benefittes. Wherefore be ready to geue than<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes to ſuch ſort of men: conli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deryng, that thou arte not choſen reuenger of the betraide ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, but Captain of thy coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trye.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="116" facs="tcp:21658:63"/>
            <head>Of treaſons by nyght, and of vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the courſe of the Starres.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or to giue an aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaulte, and to take occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to oppreſſe the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies by nyghte through treaſon, it is neadefull, that y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> haue ſome knowe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the courſe, and mouinges of the Starres, ſeing that through the ig<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>norance of ſuche thinges, the determi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nation of them, which would commit treaſon, moſte oftentymes becommeth vayne: where the Traytour hauing ſometime appoincted with thee, the thyrde or the fourthe, or what ſo euer other howre thou lyſte, the whiche he hath thought to haue been fytte, either to open the gate, or to kill ſome of the warde of the Citie, or fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally to oppreſſe at a ſudden ſome am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſhe of the enemies, not knowyng the determinate bowre, of neceſſitie it is lyke in one of theſe two thynges to committe error, eyther goyng ſooner
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:21658:63"/>then is nedefull, and before the Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour hath procured the thyng, wherby thou mayeſt be taken of the enemy, or be hindred to bryng to effect y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>, which thou haſt determined vpon, or els go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing latter, then the tyme apoincted, giue occaſion that the Traytour bee caught and kylled, and ſo be an impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diment to thy ſelfe, to bryng to paſſe the thing that y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> goeſt about. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is requiſite with iudgement, to make conſecture, and diligently conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, in what ſpace of tyme, how many voiages thou haſt to make: and then conſideryng the courſes of the ſtarres, thou muſt with thy ſelfe, moſte dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently remember how farre thou haſt gone, and howe muche there is to go: ſo that thou aryue not ſooner nor later, then the hower of the tyme appointed, and that thou bee within the wal, before the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my vnderſtande of thy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myng.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="118" facs="tcp:21658:64"/>
            <head>Of takyng by daye, a Citie or Caſtell by treaſon.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Ut if thou muſt nedes by daye go to take with treaſon a Citie or Caſtel, whyleſt thou art a marching, ſende before a parte of thy horſemenne, to take all thoſe which be founde by the waye, to the ende, that none ſtirring from the fielde, doe runne to the Citie, to geue aduyſe that thy men come to aſſaulte the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: but rather make that in a mome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t at a ſudden, thou be preſent with the enemy with thy armie in good araye. But after that ſudde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly, y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> haſt aſſalted hym, he hauing not thereof any whit of ſuſpitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, if it be not good, the thing to be done by treaſon, commaunde thy men to faight without further delay, withall force, and to goe with moſt ſpedy celeretie, to the intent to preue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t the enemie, thou hauing occaſion to approche eyther to a Caſtell or to a forte, or finallye to a Citie, and this ineſpecially, when thou ſhalt haue
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:21658:64"/>fewe men, and inferior to thoſe of the enemy. And in dede, where the ſudden brunt and vnloked for, cometh vppon them, contrary to their opinion, it is wonte greuouſly to trouble the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, although he be of greater power. But if he ſeing the men that aſſaulte hym, haue leaſure to deliberate, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king harte agayne, he wyl then begin to paſſe littell, and more boldely wyll faight: whereby it chaunceth moſt of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten tymes, that the firſt ſalies, and the beginninges of the enterpryſe, are wonte to ſeeme more fearfull, then when ſlowely &amp; with delay they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceade. For the which thyng, to manye it hath chaunced, that with a ſudden larum, the enemy nowe aſtonied and made afrayd, they haue with litle labour conſtrayned to ſubmit him ſelfe of his own mynde or els againſt his will, to render obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="120" facs="tcp:21658:65"/>
            <head>Of beſieging a Citye.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N layng the ſiege to a Citie, aboue al thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, the vertue of the captaine, is nedeful, and the policies of warre like wiſe is to be required, &amp; the preparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ordinaunce. Where alſo ought to be foreſeen and taken hede of, that thoſe, whiche thou kepeſt beſieged, in no place at a ſudden offende thee. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that they who ſee theym ſelues to be beſieged knowe, if they ſhall be negligent, what greuous hurtes, will come vppon them, for whiche cauſe, more circumſpectlye they take heede, and obſerue by what waye, they may indamage the ennemye that beſiegeth them. And ſurely, he that thinkes to be in no peril, deth ſome of thoſe thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, which he hath determined, when it pleaſeth him: but withoute doubt, who ſo euer conſidereth him ſelfe to be in daunger, ſeketh euerye occaſion, whiche founde, inforceth him ſelfe to take it, &amp; to vſe it againſt his aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. wherfore he that doth beſiege muſt
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:21658:65"/>fortifie his campe with ſtakes, with trenches, and with watches &amp; wardes. For as much as the enemy a far of, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth that which y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> prepareſt, &amp; the ſame whiche thou arte about to do: agaynſt which, thoſe whome thou kepeſt beſie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, being couered of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wal, at times iſſuing out at vnawares, &amp; out of the gates running abroade, may burne al thy artifices, &amp; Ingins, &amp; oppreſſe thy ſouldſers, &amp; ruinate whatſoeuer ſhall come to their ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des. The which thing they will not attempt to doe, if nere to the gates, as well to the great, as to the littell, where appeareth, that they may iſſue out of the Citie, thou haue placed for watche, ſome hande of thy Souldiours, who maye lette ſuch ſudden ſalies &amp; incurſions: other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, the enemies iſſuing out ſecretly, may many tymes, be able to doe lyke thinges.</p>
            <p>Very comodious and profitable it ſhal turne thee, if the enterpriſe which thou woldeſt do, ſhalbe done by night. And verely if the thyng bee doone by night, conſidering the darkenes to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which be aſſaulted, it is wont to ſeme more terrible, for that they can not diſerne, what is done. Wherby it hap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>peneth,
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:21658:66"/>peneth, that the ſuſpition is more gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous, and in the myndes increaſeth greater ferae, then if the thyng myght be ſeen. Whereof doth ryſe, ſuche vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roares and tumultes, that there is no man, which is not at his wittes end. Yea &amp; they will ſaye, that the enemy doth many thynges, which in dede he doth not, ſeing that for reſpect of the nyghte, it can not wel be vnderſtand, of what part the aſſaulte is geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with the ladders, and that which is done. Moreouer through all the Citie, they wil run vp and downe here and there, and in euery place rayſe rumors and feare, and terrible brutes or tales, for as muche as falſe feare, deuines of thinges to come, and eſtemeth it to be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame whiche ſuſpition imagineth.</p>
            <p>And euery thyng that thou doeſt by night, although it be but litle, to them which thou kepeſt beſeged, may ſeeme horrible and fearfull. For as much as none telleth that which he ſeeth: but euery man, particularly rehearſeth that, whyche in the darke he hathe hearde. And if it be vnderſtoode that of ſome part, one or twoo of the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, haue got vppon the wall, thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng thoſe to bee all the menne, put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyng
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:21658:66"/>them ſelues to flyghte, leauyng their defence, and forſaking their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifications, they will departe.</p>
            <p>If thou wylt that ſpeadelye ſome woorke be diſpatched and doone, ſee thou be the fyrſt to put to thy hande to the ſame woorke. Becauſe the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, not ſo much with threatnynges, is inforced to do that which thou wol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt, as they are moued by ſhame, and of the reuerence of their ſuperiours. And vndoubtedly when euery manne ſhall ſee the Captayne before any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, putte his hande, to the worke, and to trauayle hym ſelfe therin, then they know the thyng to haue uede of ſpedenes, and they be aſhamed not to labour, and feare to drawe backward, and nowe not as ſeruauntes and ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers ſubiect to the commaundemet of other, and of an ill wyll, but driuen of ſhame, they wyl come, and (as well as though they were called) offer theim ſelues to beare equally the burden of the labour.</p>
            <p>Although there be many and ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drye inſtrumentes of warre, and dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers the inuentions to batter and to ruinate a eitie, notwithſtanding thou nedeſt not vſe them all, but only thoſe
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:21658:67"/>which thou mayſt commodiouſly. And without doubt, if I ſhoulde vndertake to teach thee, I were not able to name all thoſe, which are to be occupied, I meane the Aries, the Teſtudini the Vinie, the Baliſtes, the Bridges, and ſuch lyke woorke and Ingins: for as much as ſuche thinges, appertaine to the riches and power of theim that make the warre, and alſo to the witti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of the Architecturres, and Artifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, and vnto the cunning and ſubtil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes in artificially making them. But that whiche aboue all thing, agreeth wyth the prudence of a Captaine, me thinkes is ſpecially to choſe ſome parte of the citie, or caſtell, where like workes &amp; ordinaunce may be brought vnto. For that thou canſt not caſelye compas all the citie about, and aſſault all partes thereof, with woorkes and Ingins, except the caſtell were very ſmal and litle. Then hauing deuided thy men into ſundry partes, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed them by order, thou ſhalt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d that larums be geuen to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other places of the citie, &amp; that ſchaling lad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders be alſo brought to the wall, ſo that the citezins maye knowe to bee oppreſſed on euery ſde, &amp; through ſuch
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:21658:67"/>difficultie to be conſtrayned, that they can not well deliberate to what parte of the Citie they ought to geue ſuccour. Seyng that if the other partes be aba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned and that they ſhall attende to the ſame, whereunto the Ingins are planted, the Souldiours beyng made ready to the ſchallyng, not letted of any man, with facelety may get vpon the wall: or els if the townes men de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiding them ſelues through al places, wyll euery one according to his ſtren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gthe, do the beſt they can to defende: thoſe which ſhalbe placed againſt the violence of the Ingins, and inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes of warre, can not being but a fewe, ſuſteine the wayghtines of the fayghte, nor repulſe the fury of ſo hote and terrible aſſault.</p>
            <p>Wherfore it ſhalbe to very good pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe &amp; profitable, to make as though in diuers places thou wouldeſt aſſault the city, ſo that through the ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dry pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parations, and for the dyuers maners to ouercome it, thou deuide in manye partes the force, and the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rels of the Citezins, and keepe their myndes troubled, and here and there to drawe and retyre them. Whereby thou in this mean while, of that part,
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:21658:68"/>which with all thy power ſhalt ſtande intentiue to faight, more eaſely mayſt oppreſſe the Citie, and take it, as it were a certayne body.</p>
            <p>But if thu makeſt haſte, and infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſt thy ſelfe ſpeadely to wynne ſome Caſtel or Citie, or els ſome Forte, and that thou ſeeſt nowe thy Souldiours through labour to be weery, and that it ſhoulde not tourne thee well to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre the enterpryſe, nor to remoue the Souldiours from the fayght, then it is nedefull for thee, to deuyde thy men into ſundrye orders, hauyng re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecte to the number of them, and to the greatnes of the Citie.</p>
            <p>And beginning in the fyrſt watche of the nyght, the tyme to fayght being equally deuided betwene them, the ſquadrons with equal ſpace put in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, boldlye vndertake the enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pryſe. And after the firſt warde, cauſe the ſeconde, to ſuccede, and the thyrde next the ſame, and the fourth, and the fifte alſo, if ſo many ſhall nede: rely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing nowe the one, &amp; nowe the other. So that whiles y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> one ſquadron faigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, the other may ordinarely repoſe them ſelues &amp; ſlepe. Finally the night ended, in the beginning of the daye, re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>turne
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:21658:68"/>the very ſame order: &amp; ſo retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning from time to time, continue the enterpriſe, diſtributing the handes &amp; deuidyng them, courſe by courſe. In which maner, ſhal happe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> two things, which is, that day and night without any delay of time, they ſhall faighte, &amp; thoſe which are wery, ſhalbe reliued of the luſty, refreſhed throughe reſt, which by their tourne they haue take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Nor let no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thinke, that citizens be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieged, can vſe the ſelfe ſame councell, and that diſpoſed with the ſame order, although thei be many, may with like maner &amp; w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> exchau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ging now the one, now the other, without diſturbance &amp; moſt great labour, defende the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues. For as much as euery man, which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membreth to ſtande in perill, albeit he ſuppoſeth that the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>moditie is geuen him to ſlepe, neuertheleſſe he can take no reſt. For that conſidering the dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger that ſtandeth him vpon, he is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained to watche, as though the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie wers like to go in ruin in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> meane time that he ſlepeth &amp; repoſeth himſelf</p>
            <p>But peraduenture ſome wyll ſaye, what? thynkeſt thou that the Captaine is made of a Diamant, or elles of Steale? Whyche in all thoſe
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:21658:69"/>thynges, that by the ſpace of courſe be to all the armie deuyded, he onelye continually ought to ſtand vigilant, &amp; neuer him ſelfe to take reſt. Surely I do not ſeke this of him, nor forbidde not that at a time he geue himſelfe to quietnes &amp; to ſlepe, ſo that he do it mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derately, and that the ſlepe be ſhort: &amp; in that while, do chuſe ſome faithfull and valiaunt manne, which for repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacion and authoritye, hath the ſecond place, after the Captain, and the char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge of gouerning to be geuen him.</p>
            <p>Sometime thoſe partes of the Citie which be of ſome high rocke, &amp; dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſnes, or els otherwiſe fortified of nature, hath ben ſeen to haue geuen to thoſe who haue ouercome them, grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter occaſion to take and win the citie, then ſuche walles haue done, whyche wyth arte, and with hands haue bene made ſure and ſtrong, &amp; therefore they are reputed, to be more weake. And in dede thoſe places that be fortified by nature, are wont to be kept more neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly, with none, or but with a ſmal gariſon of Souldiers: And in this caſe the wiſe and wittie Captaine truſting in ſuche occaſion, maye ſtudy and find out, that whiche is to be done: and
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:21658:69"/>wyth rewardes and wyth promiſes, ſeke to induſe ſome of his men which are moſt bolde, that they inforce them ſelues eyther with ladders, or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, to get vp on that parte, where is moſt adoe to clime. And yf peraduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture they ſhalbe gotten vp, and ſecret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye entered within the wall. Let them take ſome gate of the Citie, whether it be great or litle: and inforce theym ſelues to open it, and to kepe it open. And to this thing ſhalbe of moſt great helpe, if in ſome maner, they ſhal from without, draw vppe to the wall, ſome trumpet, the which in a ſudden ſhould begin to ſounde. For that the enemy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es hearing the trumpet from the wal, and ineſpecially by night, it ſhall put great feare in the myndes of the Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens, thinking now y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> city to be take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; them ſelues altogether to be ouercom: wherby being made afraide, they wil forſake the gates, and the places of watche and warde, and take theim to their heles, that way, which they ſhal thinke moſt mete. Wherfore to thy o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Souldiers, whiche looke for the ende of the thyng, it wylbe eaſye, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing no manner of incounter, eyther
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:21658:70"/>the gates being broken to enter, or els with ladders to get vppon the wall. In this maner with one trumpet, and the ſame vnarmed, thou mayeſt take and wynne a Citie.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>Of the Citie taken.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>F thou take a ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty which for the number &amp; worthines of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> citize<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, are thought puiſaunt, whereby is to bee fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, leaſt they drawing together with often turning backe, ſetting them ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues againſt thy menne, do make reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaunce, or els keping the higheſt pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and afterwarde from thence ſore hurt thy Souldiers, or els at the ende retire in ſome hold, from whenſe after accordyng to occaſyon they may yſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue out to geue thee the aſſault, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt the thing ſhalbe in ſuch caſe, thou muſt openly cauſe to be vnderſtoode, that who ſo euer ſhal lay downe their weapons, and willyngly vnarm them ſelues, by no manner of wife ſhall be killed of thy ſouldiers. Becauſe euery man ſekes firſte to do to other that, which he thinkes, ſhal happen to him
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:21658:70"/>ſelf, when ſo euer he is taken, &amp; therin he doth inforce him ſelfe, to preuent o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Whereby hath happened, that ſome often tymes by force, haue dry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen out the ennemies nowe diſperſed in the taken Citie, or els, if they were not able ſo to doe, they haue retyred in ſome exceading ſtrong Rocke, ſo that a new they haue hadde power to geue trauaile and labour to their enemyes, after ſuche ſort, that the aduerſaries haue been driuen to a new ſiege, and ſomtime much longer &amp; more difficult then y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt, paſſing through many pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rils. And maye chaunce, by publiſhing thy decree in euery place, al or at leſt wiſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> greater part, wil caſt doun their weapo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. For y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thoſe which are ſo dyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainfull againſt the enemy, that they deſire with force of armes to attempt fortune, hauyng ſuſpicyon whether the other Citizens be of the ſame diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition or not, will come alſo to laye downe their weapons. And by this it happeneth, that albeit that euery one of them would vſe their weapons, and trie their ſtrengthes, notwithſtanding particularly, the one hauing ſuſpition of the other, they wyll all make haſte to lay down their weapons, euery man douting to remain himſelf only armed
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:21658:71"/>ſeyng that the ſhortnes of tyme, and of thinges doth not permit that they may manifeſt a newe their myndes, and then to take councell. Neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, thoſe whiche haue deſire to ſaue theym ſelues, and that all manner of wayes do attende to their owne ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard, tyll ſuche time as ſome hope of the ſame be offred and ſhewed theim, althoughe with veruent minde for their ſafety they would yelde, yet con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained of verye neceſſitye, they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſte thoſe that come to hurt them. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit when they fynde but litle hope of ſafegarde, then of proud enemyes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comming humble with prayers, they wilbe gladde to ſeke thee. Whereby with like decree thou ſhalt induce alſo to laye downe their weapons, thoſe whiche by force of armes haue deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined to defende themſelues.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>Of ſtaying the reuenge against thoſe which are ouercome.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He death which chaunſeth to ſouldiers faighting, in no maner of wiſe hath nede, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of comfort, nor of
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:21658:71"/>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſſion, as the ſame which hath hap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned through loue of vertue &amp; for deſire to ouercom. But after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> obtained vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory, hauing nowe wonne and taken the citie, the kylling in euery place the ouercommed, is to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>querours a thing moſte miſerable, and rather then ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, a teſtimony of crueltie and fooliſh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes. And although thou be angered &amp; made cruel againſt the ouercommed &amp; ſubdued, y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> muſt not therefore thynke, to ſuffer harme, either of thy reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or of thy affayres, if the enemies ſo ſone as they are oppreſſed, haue not been ſiayne. For that leyſurely at thy commoditie, all perril of faighting ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken awaye, thou mayeſt deliberate, what thou wilt do with the ennemie that thou haſt conquered.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>Of the Citie whiche by force of Armes can not be ouercome.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F thou haue not hope to be able to ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come and take by force of Armes, the ſame Citie
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:21658:72"/>that thou haſte beſieged, and that for ſuch occaſion, thou muſte prolong the ſiege, and that neuertheleſſe it is to be iudged, that by length of time, &amp; by fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine thou maiſt get ſuch a Citie, thou ſhalt cauſe to be taken in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Countrie, and in the fieldes, as manye as thou findeſt, and of theſe chuſe theym, whyche for valiauntnes of minde, for iuſtines of bodye, and for floriſhing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of age, ſhal ſeme vnto thee apt for the war, whom thou mayſt vſe where ſhall tourne thee to commoditie, and when thou knoweſt them to be profy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table in thy affaires. But the women, the chyldren, the olde folke, and thoſe which by other occaſion be weak, and not mere to faight, thou ſhalt inforce to enter into the Citye, as thoſe why<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che can not woorke, nor helpe in anye thing the ſame, which for the defence of a City is deſired, ſo that they much ſoner conſuming the vittailes, may be of ſo great harme to the beſieged citizens, that they may be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted a great deale ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner ennemies, then frendes, or ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boures.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="135" facs="tcp:21658:72"/>
            <head>Of the behauiour, vvhych the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine ought to vſe, after the VVarre is ended.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter that the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fayres of warre, vnder thy gouernment is done and ended, ſo that, the ſame acclompliſhed, thou haue lybertie to make an ende of all thinges, ſhew not thy ſelfe proud and ſeuere, but rather humble, pleaſant, &amp; gentle, and conſequently, louing to al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>men. For as muche as the firſte thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, bredes enuye, and the other in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duceth emulacion and affection. En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uye, is the hauing griefe &amp; ſorowe at the proſperitie of other: and emulaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is the deſire to folow the vertue of other. But they be betwene theym ſo contrarye, that he whych hath en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uy, deſireth that none haue any good. And he that hath emulacion, hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyre to bryng to paſſe in lyke maner, ſuche thynges, as other by them ſelues haue honorably attained.</p>
            <p>Then a man of a good minde ſhall
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:21658:73"/>not onelye be a good guyde of armed men: and of a countrye, but alſo a wiſe Captayne, a dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gente preſeruer and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernor, in augmenting his honor and in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruing the ſame perpetuallye withoute any pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rill.</p>
         </div>
         <trailer>The ende.</trailer>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:21658:73"/>
            <head>¶ THE TABLE OF the principall thinges which in this booke are contained.</head>
            <p>FOr what occaſyon menne faight vnfortunately. fol. iii.</p>
            <p>The Romaynes through prudence, by councel, and with the feates of war, obtayned the Empire of the world. fol. iiii.</p>
            <p>They, which attribute all infclicity only to fortune, are fooles and very ſunple. fol. iiii.</p>
            <p>It is the property of a malicious and vniuſt man, to excuſe him from euery fault, which hath miniſtred euill the publyke affaires. fol. iiii.</p>
            <p>In chooſyng a Generall Capytaine, no reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect ought to be had, neyther to his ſtocke, nor to his predeceſſours, nor to his fortunatnes in riches. fol. vii.</p>
            <p>The qualitye whiche ought to be in a Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Captaine. fol. viii.</p>
            <p>He that is not geuen to couetouſnes of golde and ſiluer, maye honorablye haue the charge of the affaires of warre. fol. x.</p>
            <p>The Captaine ought to be neyther olde nor yonge. fol. x.</p>
            <p>He that hath children, is meete to be choſen Captaine. fol. xii.</p>
            <p>The Captaine ought to be a faire ſpeaker. fol. xii.</p>
            <p>More difficulte it is, to cure the infirmiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es that ſtandeth hid, then thoſe whiche bothe maye be felt and ſeene. fol. xiii.</p>
            <p>The Captaine that is to be choſen, ought to be a man well eſremed &amp; of reputacion. fol. xiiii.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:21658:74"/>
            <p>The poore Captaine, ſo that he be good and valiaunt, is not to be refuſed. fol. xiiii.</p>
            <p>The Captain intentiue to gaine money, is not good. fol. xv.</p>
            <p>In a Captaine, his reputacion, and the noby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of his predeceſſors is to be eſtemed. fol. xvi</p>
            <p>By reaſon it is to be thought, that he is more lyke to be a better Captayne that is no gentel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man borne, then ſome of noble pare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tage. fol. xvii</p>
            <p>The Captaine ſhoulde be choſen valyaunt, of noble bloude, aduenturous, &amp; rich. fol. xviii</p>
            <p>The headdes of the Souldiers woulde be ſtrong, bolde, &amp; faithful to their country. fol. xx</p>
            <p>It is much vtility to the common weale, to ſet forwarde the nobilitie, when an enterpriſe muſt be done, and in doing the ſame, is required ſpedines. fol. xx.</p>
            <p>The Captaine ought to haue with him ſome Counſellers and companions. fol. xxi.</p>
            <p>He often tunes committes errour, whych not minding to heare the aduiſe of other, doeth at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute euery thing to him ſelfe alone. fol. xxii.</p>
            <p>The weake beginninges of thinges, cannot ſuſtain y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> burthen of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is ſaid vpon them. fo. xxv</p>
            <p>Of the maner that is to be vſed in the bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing foorth the army. fol. xxvi.</p>
            <p>Throughe euerye place, the armye ought to marche in battel raye. fol. xxvi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <p>Always it is better and more ſure, and much caſyer, to gouerne the battaile which marcheth cloſe together, and ſquare, then thynne and longe. fol. xxix.</p>
            <p>The victuales, the cariages, and all the rem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunt of prouiſion, ought to be pleaed in the midſt of the army. fol. xxx.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:21658:74"/>
            <p>Through dearth of victuales, and for lacke of money, warres are wonte to abate, and to extinguiſhe. fol. xxxii.</p>
            <p>It woulde be cared for, with al diligence, that to the Campe, both by ſea and land, the victual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les may ſafely be brought fol. xxxiiii.</p>
            <p>The lodginges being placed, diches and tren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches muſt be made. fol. xxxv.</p>
            <p>It is a holſome and a profitable thing, not to kepe an army to long in one continuall place. fol. xxxvi.</p>
            <p>The ſtanding in ydlenes, and in ſlouthful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, cauſes the bodyes to become weake and languiſhed, and diſpoſeth their nundes altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vile and fearefull. fol. xxxvii.</p>
            <p>The army inſtructed, and ſet in araye, ought to be deuided into .ii. partes. fol. xli.</p>
            <p>The Captaine muſt praiſe them, the whiche haue alwayes defended their places. fol. xlii.</p>
            <p>Souldyers ought not to be ſuffred, which pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumpteouſly go to robbe and ſpoile. fol. xliiii</p>
            <p>Euery manne muſt ſtand on his feete to kepe watche and ward. fol. xlvii</p>
            <p>The armye mindyng ſecretlye to departe, ought to make many fires. fol. xlviii.</p>
            <p>The fugetiues are to be kept in ward. fo. xlix</p>
            <p>The wiſe Captayne oughte wyth all dily<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence to vew the Campe of the euemies. fol. l.</p>
            <p>Wyth thoſe wayes, whiche maye beguile the ennemye, with the verye ſame it is to be taken hede of, not to be deceyued. fol. lv.</p>
            <p>Councels are not to be diſcloſed. fol. lv.</p>
            <p>It is a ſigne of an vndiſcrete and fooliſh man, arrogantlye to manifeſt his councell to euerye man. fol. ivi.</p>
            <p>Before the Army ſhould be brought foorth.
<pb facs="tcp:21658:75"/>Sacrifice would be done. fol. lvii.</p>
            <p>Knowledge of places muſt be had. fol. ix.</p>
            <p>In conducting foorthe menne of Armes, it is to be foreſene, that by the ſelfe ſame way where they entered, it may be open to returne. fol. lxii.</p>
            <p>Souldiers refreſhed with meat, become more ſtrong and luſty. fol. lxvi.</p>
            <p>The countenance of the Capitayne, is wonte to make the myndes of the Souidyers confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable. fol. lxvii.</p>
            <p>When the Armye ought to be put in terrour. fol. lxix.</p>
            <p>Howe Souldiers may be incouraged wyth the priſoners of the enemye. fol. lxxi.</p>
            <p>Howe men are ſet in araye. fol. lxxiii.</p>
            <p>To auoide, that the enemy compaſſe thee not. fol. lxxviii.</p>
            <p>Of that, whiche appertayneth to a prudent Captayne, when he hath to faight with a fewe men, againſt a great multitude. fol. lxxix.</p>
            <p>The aſſaulting the enemyes behinde at vna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wares, putteth them in moſt great terrour, and is of incredible profite. fol. lxxxv.</p>
            <p>The office of a wyſe Capitayne is, to place to gether in the rankes, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> brethren with brothers, and feendes with frendes, fol. lxxxvi.</p>
            <p>Of Commaundementes, wauinges, and ſignes. fol. lxxxvii.</p>
            <p>Of the order that ought to be obſerued. fol. xc.</p>
            <p>Nothing is better, more ſafer, nor more ſurer, then for men to obſerue order, and to ſtande ſtil in their place. fol. xci.</p>
            <p>The cryes, the noyſe of armour, and the ſound of trompettes, wonderfullye troubleth and feareth the mindes of the enemyes. fol. xci.</p>
            <p>The Capitaine often tymes, ſeyng the prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation
<pb facs="tcp:21658:75"/>of the enemies, is conſtrained to accomo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>date, and to ordayne his men according to the armours, the men &amp; maner of the ſame. fol. xciii.</p>
            <p>It is not a laudable thing for a Capitayne, to caſt him ſelfe with all his men, into the handes of chaunce. fol. xcv.</p>
            <p>In a thing vncertayne, it is better with bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, not onelye to auoyde the ouerthrowe, but alſo to ſeke to hurt the enemy. fol. xcv.</p>
            <p>The office of the Capitayne whyleſt the battaile is a faightyng. fol. xcviii</p>
            <p>Many tymes the death of the Capitaine hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, the reputation of fortunate ſucceſſes doe upayre fol. Ci.</p>
            <p>Of that, which the Capitaine hath to doe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the deede of Armes. fol. Ciii.</p>
            <p>The Souldiers ought to be partakers of the gayne. fol. Ciiii.</p>
            <p>So long as the warre laſteth, the priſoners ought not to be put to death. fol. Cvi.</p>
            <p>The feaſtes and triumphes, after the victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. fol. Cvii.</p>
            <p>Of burying them which in the battayle haue bene ſlayne. fol. Cviii.</p>
            <p>Often tymes the happy ſucces of the act, hath bene of greater damage, then the receiued ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw. fol. Cix.</p>
            <p>To feare, where is nedefull, and when the time requires, is the property of a man, whiche politikely foreſees his buſines. fol. C. x.</p>
            <p>It is a ſtraunge, and fooliſhe thing, a man not to defende him ſelfe from perrtiles. fol. Cxii.</p>
            <p>Howe the Capitayne oughte to behaue him ſelfe to bringe a Citye to yeide. fol. Cxiii.</p>
            <p>Nothing filleth the myndes of men ſo muche with vakantnes, as the iminente feare of pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryll.
<pb facs="tcp:21658:76"/>fol. Exiiii.</p>
            <p>All profes, whiche is made againſt deſperate men, are difficult and perilous. fol. Cxiiii.</p>
            <p>Fidelity is to be vſed with traytors. fol. Exv.</p>
            <p>Of treaſon by nighte, &amp; of vnderſtanding the courſe of the ſtarres. fol. Exvi.</p>
            <p>A way to take by day, a City or caſtle by trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. fol. Exviii.</p>
            <p>The ſodayne inuaſions, and not looked for, comming vpon men, contrary to their opinion, are wont greuouſly to trouble y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> enemy. fol. Cxix</p>
            <p>In laying ſege to a City, aboue all thinges, the vertue of the capitayn is moſt nedeful. fol. Cxx.</p>
            <p>The thing that is done by nighte, is wont to ſeeme moſt terrible. fol. Cxxi</p>
            <p>The multitude, not ſo muche wyth threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninges is compelled to do thinges, as they are moued with ſhame, &amp; of the reuerence towardes their ſuperiours. fol. Cxxiii</p>
            <p>The Capitaine ought when time requires, to make ſuch a truſtye man his deputy, which for reputatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; auctority is next to him. fol. cxxviii.</p>
            <p>The reuenge, is to be forborne againſt thoſe that haue bene ouercome. fol. Cxxxii.</p>
            <p>The way y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to be vſed to take a city, which by force of armes cannot be ouercome. fo. cxxxiiii</p>
            <p>Of the behauior which the Capitaine ought to vſe after the war is ended. fol. Cxxxv.</p>
            <p>How enuy is to haue grieft of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> proſperity of other: and howe emulation, is the deſire to imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate the vertue of other men. fol. Cxxxv.</p>
            <trailer>The ende of the Table.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="colophon">
            <pb facs="tcp:21658:76"/>
            <p>¶ Imprynted at London, by Wyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyam Seres, dwellinge at the Weſt end of Pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, at the ſygne of the Hedge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hogge.</p>
            <p>¶ Cum priuilegio ad imprimen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum ſolum.</p>
            <p>Anno. 1563.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:21658:77" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21658:77" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:21658:78"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21658:78"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:21658:79"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:21658:79"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:21658:80"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:21658:80"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:21658:81"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21658:81"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:21658:82"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:21658:82"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:21658:83"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:21658:83"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:21658:84"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:21658:84"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:21658:85"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:21658:85"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:21658:86"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:21658:86"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:21658:87"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:21658:87"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:21658:88"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:21658:88"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:21658:89"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:21658:89"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:21658:90"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:21658:90"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:21658:91"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:21658:91"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:21658:92"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:21658:92"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:21658:93"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:21658:93"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:21658:94"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:21658:94"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
